<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="emblem" n="e48"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
                <pb n="149"/><!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                
                
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>
                        <lb/>Embleme 48. Of the Secrets of Nature.
                        <lb/>The King falls sicke by drinking water, and is restored to health
                        <lb/>by Physicians.
                    </head>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Epigramme 48.</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>In wealth nor people dos the King delight,</l>
                        <l>Soe much as to have water brought in sight.</l>
                        <l>Cup after cup hee drinks, growes swelld and wanne</l>
                        <l>Urging releife from his Physician,</l>
                        <l>Where finding art by various means essayd,</l>
                        <l>His health restord and tumor was allayd.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                
                
                <pb n="150"/> <!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Discourse 48.</head>
                    <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                        <lb/>Xerxes that most potent King of Persia leading his army through dry<pc>-</pc><milestone unit="section" n="e03-01" /> <!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                        <lb/>and rugged places in hott weather, being thirsty, refused not a draught<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>of muddy water offered by a souldier, but dranke most freely, and rewarded
                        <lb/>him that brought it very amply. And indeed if a man at this very time
                        <lb/>(as some of the latest historians affirme) travell through the borders of
                        <lb/>Persia, it is sayd that fountains of sweet water are very rarely found,
                        <lb/>standing waters being brackish, and the Soyle itselfe in the surface<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>yeilding much saltnesse: After the same manner the King, which the
                        <lb/>Philosophers have made mention of being perplexed with thirst, com
                        <lb break="no"/>manded plenty of sweet water to be brought him, of which hee dranke
                        <lb/>his fill; as if manifest to any man by the Allegory of Merlinus. The
                        <lb/>cure of the sicke and discoloured King is undertaken by severall Physi
                        <lb break="no"/>tians: The Ægyptians administring their medicines stirred the humors
                        <lb/>being yet crude, which Hippocrates affirms ought to be purged being<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>first concocted, unlesse they be fluxible and uncertaine: For then they
                        <lb/>must be forthwith expelled, that they may not peradventure make an
                        <lb/>assault upon the more noble parts or bowells. Hereupon dangerous Symp
                        <lb break="no"/>toms, such as Hipothymy and Syncope happened to the King, but the Phy
                        <lb break="no"/>sicians of Alexandria coming last of all, and esteemed more successfull
                        <lb/>in a chronicke disease, restored the King to his former health. It is well<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>worth while to cure soe great a King, who being made sound extends a
                        <lb/>liberall hand and a serene aspect to his Physician. Wee have read that<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>many mens cures have been very nobly rewarded by severall Kings, as<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>that of Domocides by Polycrates a tyrant of Samos with two talents, of
                        <lb/>Erasiscratus (who, as Pliny writes, was Schollar of Chrysippus, begotten<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>upon the daughter of Aristotle) for curing King Antiochus being sicke
                        <lb/>for the love of his Stepmother Stratonice, with a hundred talents by his
                        <lb/>Sonne Ptolemy, of Jacob Cocterius, Physician of Lewis the 2d <!-- unsure if this is right --> King of<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>France, from whome hee receivd four thousand Crowns every moneth as
                        <lb/>a stipend, and other later wee make noe mention of; but the cure of
                        <lb/>this King is recompensed with yet a farre greater gratuity or reward. For
                        <lb/>thus say Hermes and Geber in the Rosary: Hee that hath once com
                        <lb break="no"/>pleted this art, if hee should live ten hundred thousand years, and<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>every day feed four thousand men, would not want. This Senior con
                        <lb break="no"/>firms, saying: Hee that hath that stone, whereof the Elixir is made
                        <lb/>is soe rich, as hee that hath fire, can give fire, to whome hee will, and<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>when hee will, and as much as hee will without his owne detriment or want.
                        <lb/>The father of Democritus was soe rich, that hee gave a feast to the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>army of Xerxes, and Pythius a man exceding wealthy offered to the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>same pay for his whole army, and victuall for five moneths, provided<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>that the youngest of his five sonns, which was the comfort of his old<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>age, might be permitted to stay at home, and not be constraind to goe<pc>-</pc>
                        
                        
                        
                        <pb n="151"/><fw>Discourse 48.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                        <lb/>into the Kings army, but the barbarous King taking the petition of Pythius
                        <lb/>most unworthily, comanded his younger sonne to be cutt in two peices,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>and fastened to stakes on both sides the high way, by which his whole ar
                        <lb break="no"/>my was to passe, as Sabellicus observes in booke 2. Ennead 3. but the riches
                        <lb/>of these men are nothing to the riches of our King, which are without<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>dimension and number. Being cured and freed from the waters all the
                        <lb/>Kings, and Potentates of other regions did honour and fear him: And when
                        <lb/>they were willing to see any of his wonderfull works, they putt one<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>ounce of Mercury well washd in a crucible, and cast thereupon (as it were
                        <lb/>one graine of Millet seed) of his nayls, or of his harre or blood, and<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>blowd gently with coales, they let it coole with them, and found such a
                        <lb/>stone as I know. This is hee, whome Count Bernhard mentioneth, that<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>gives to his six courtiers soe much of his kingdome, as hee himselfe possesseth,
                        <lb/>provided they waite, till hee recover youth in the bath, and be adorned<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>with various garments, namely, a blacke breast=plate, a white shirt, and
                        <lb/>purple blood; for then hee promiseth to give some of his blood to every
                        <lb/>one, and make them partakers of his riches<pc>. . . . . . . .</pc>
                    </ab>   
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>