<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="emblem" n="e14"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
                <pb n="47"/><!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                
                
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>
                        <lb/>Embleme 14. Of the Secrets of Nature.
                        <lb/>This is the Dragon which devours his tayle.
                    </head>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Epigramme 14.</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>Hunger taught Polypus his flesh to eat,</l>
                        <l>And man with man his appetite to treat:</l>
                        <l>The hungry Dragon feeding on his tayle,</l>
                        <l>His fainting soule releives, which els would fayle;</l>
                        <l>Hold him to hard meat, till himselfe hee doe</l>
                        <l>Eat and devoure, kill and revive anew.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                
                
                <pb n="48"/> <!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Discourse 14.</head>
                    <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                        <lb/>It is a saying of the Ancients, that a Serpent, which hath devourd a Serpent, be<milestone unit="section" n="e03-01" /> <!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                        <lb break="no"/>comes a Dragon: for it is cruell to its kind, as a theife and Murderer to his: It is
                        <lb/>evident that such are in Africa, of soe great bignesse and plenty, that they
                        <lb/>destroyed a great part of Alexanders army: Amongst the Asachaei a people
                        <lb/>of Aethiopia are very great produced, which being wrapd together after
                        <lb/>the manner of hurdles doe with their heads lifted up make way to better
                        <lb/>pasture. They report that the Kings of India maintaind two Dragons, one
                        <lb/>of eighty, and the other of minely cubits in bignesse: by the observation of
                        <lb/>later writers and now adayes it is knowne, that near Angola are found such
                        <lb/>as are aequall to the great masts of ships: Soe they report that in some cer
                        <lb break="no"/>taine mountains of India and Africa there is great store of gold, but kept by
                        <lb/>dragons, lest any one come thither and take it away: For dragons doe resort
                        <lb/>to fountains or rivers, which fall from the mountains, and soe are sayd to watch
                        <lb/>the gold by accident: for this reason doe the Philosophers ascribe soe many
                        <lb/>dragons or serpents to their treasures, as to the golden Fleece, the garden of the
                        <lb/>Hesperides, and to other persons or Chymicall subjects, to Cadmus, Saturne, Aescu
                        <lb break="no"/>lapius, Mercury, whose wand is begirt with two serpents, make and female: but
                        <lb/>doe they meane nothing els by Dragons, but Chymicall subjects? Hereupon
                        <lb/>say they, the Dragons yeild mountains, and the earth fountains to Rebis,
                        <lb/>and denoting the extreme hunger of the dragon in devouring his tayle: which
                        <lb/>though others may interpret of the year returning into itselfe, and resembling
                        <lb/>a circle, yet it was accomodated by the Philosophers to their things, who
                        <lb/>by this dragon would have a Serpent understood, which devoures another of
                        <lb/>its owne kind, and this is properly called Sulphur, as they all attest in innume
                        <lb break="no"/>rable places: Lully in his little booke chapt. 31. This is, sayth hee, Sulphur,
                        <lb/>my Sonne! and this the serpent and dragon devouring his tayle, the roar
                        <lb break="no"/>ing lyon, and sharp sword, cutting, mortifying, and tearing all things. And
                        <lb/>the Rosary: The Dragon dyes not, unlesse hee be killd with his brother
                        <lb/>and sister. And a little after: The Dragon is Argent vive extracted from
                        <lb/>bodyes, having in it a body, soule, and spirit: This is in the same place
                        <lb/>called by another name ffectid <!-- odd spelling -->water, which is produced after the separation
                        <lb/>of the Elements: Now the Dragon is sayd to devour his tayle, in consuming
                        <lb/>the voluble, venomous, and moist part, that after without a tayle hee
                        <lb/>may seem more corpulent and of lesse speed, for the motion and volu
                        <lb break="no"/>bility of him consisted cheifely in his tayle: Other animalls depend upon
                        <lb/>feet, but dragons, serpents, and wormes of that kind doe use constriction and
                        <lb/>explication of body instead of feet, and as it were water poure out doe di
                        <lb break="no"/>vide into certaine courses, inclining themselves sometimes this way some
                        <lb break="no"/>times that, as you may see in allmost all rivers, how they turne their
                        <lb/>courses like serpents, and runne obliguely in circuits: they did not there
                        <lb break="no"/>fore without reason call Argent vive a Serpent, and and add serpents to Mer
                        <lb break="no"/>cury, it allso drawing as it were a tayle, and running sometimes this
                        <lb/>sometimes that way with a voluble poise: For as a Serpent creeps soe
                        <lb/>allso Mercury, who hath therefore wings upon his feet and head.
                        
                        
                        
                        <pb n="49"/><fw>Discourse 14.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                        <lb/>In Affrica they say are flying Serpents, which would waste and depopu
                        <lb break="no"/>late all things, if they were not destroyd by the bird calld Ibis: For which
                        <lb/>cause Ibis is erected amongst the sacred Aegyptian images, both for the mani
                        <lb break="no"/>fest utility, which it performes to the whole country, and for an occult
                        <lb/>reason, which very few men have understood. This dragon biting of his
                        <lb/>tayle, and casting his old skinne is sayd to acquire a new one together with
                        <lb/>youth, as nature hath granted longer life not onely to Crows, Ravens, Eagles,
                        <lb/>and Harts, but allso to the Serpentine kind: The Ant growing old acquireth
                        <lb/>wings, soe allso many wormes: Man growing old is put into the earth, but
                        <lb/>being revived from the earth will be consecrated to aeternall life. Of every
                        <lb/>Serpent burned is made a powder, which is taken safely against all poy
                        <lb break="no"/>sons with great effect: Such an Alexipharmacum ought allso to be made
                        <lb/>of this dragon (who hath allready devoured his tayle, which is usually cutt
                        <lb/>of in Vipers) a most effectuall remedy against the adversityes of for
                        <lb break="no"/>tune and body
                        
                    </ab>   
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

