<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="emblem" n="e12"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
                <pb n="41"/><!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                
                
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>
                        <lb/><orig>Embleme</orig> 12. Of the Secrets of Nature.
                        <lb/>The Stone, which <orig>Saturne</orig> vomited up, being devoured instead
                        <lb/>of his <orig>Sonne</orig> jupiter, is placed in Helicon as a monument to men.
                    </head>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
                    <head><orig>Epigramme</orig> 12.</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>Know would you why the Poets <choice><orig>soe</orig><reg>so</reg></choice> recount</l>
                        <l>The fame of Helicon, the Muses mount?</l>
                        <l>That <choice><orig>monumentall</orig><reg>monumental</reg></choice> stone is <choice><orig>plac'd</orig><reg>placed</reg></choice> thereon,</l>
                        <l>Which <orig>Saturne</orig> <choice><orig>gorg'd</orig><reg>gorged</reg></choice> instead of Jove his <orig>Sonne</orig>.</l>
                        <l>Be wise, the sense agrees not wish the Sound,</l>
                        <l>For Saturn's Stone in <orig>Chymistry</orig> is found.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                
                
                <pb n="42"/> <!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Discourse 12.</head>
                    <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                        <lb/>The Allegory of <orig>Saturne</orig> <orig>wee</orig> find to be taken <choice><orig>divers</orig><reg>diverse</reg></choice> <choice><orig>wayes</orig><reg>ways</reg></choice>: for the Astro<milestone unit="section" n="e03-01" /> <!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                        <lb break="no"/>nomers repute him the highest of the <choice><orig>Planetts</orig><reg>Planets</reg></choice> in order; the young students
                        <lb/>of <orig>Chymistry</orig> the meanest of <orig>metalls</orig>, namely lead: The heathen Poets: <choice><orig>con
                        <lb break="no"/>ceivd</orig><reg>conceived</reg></choice> him to be the father of Jupiter, <orig>Sonne</orig> of Cælum; the Mythologists time.
                        <lb/>But though all these may seem to have thought aright in their sense, yet<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>they will not declare those things which are <orig>elswhere</orig> spoken of <orig>Saturne</orig>,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>why <orig>hee</orig> devoured and vomited up his <orig>sonns</orig>, and a stone instead of Jupiter,
                        <lb/>why <orig>hee</orig> is the discoverer of truth, why appearing with a <choice><orig>sieth</orig><reg>scythe</reg></choice>, a serpent,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>blacknesse</orig>, morosity, and distorted feet? Herein the last <orig>thinke</orig> themselves to
                        <lb/>interpret best, saying, that time revealed and manifests truth, slided away as a Ser
                        <lb break="no"/>pent, cuts all things <orig>downe</orig> with death as by a <choice><orig>sieth</orig><reg>scythe</reg></choice>, devoured its children, that is,
                        <lb/>all those things which it <orig>hath</orig> generated, digests hard stones, or cannot consume
                        <lb/>them, and therefore <orig>dos</orig> as it were vomit them up <orig>againe</orig>: These things <orig>doe</orig> indeed
                        <lb/>agree in part, but are not consonant to the truth of the thing, and all circum
                        <lb break="no"/>stances. But the exercises Philosophers <orig>doe</orig> say, that <orig>Saturne</orig> is first in their
                        <lb/><orig>worke</orig>, which if <orig>hee</orig> be really <orig>præsent</orig>, they cannot <choice><orig>erre</orig><reg>err</reg></choice>, truth is discovered in
                        <lb/><orig>darknesse</orig>; but there is nothing besides <orig>blacknesse</orig>: wherefore they say in<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Turba Philosophorum, whatsoever <orig>colour</orig> comes after <orig>blacknesse</orig> is laudable:
                        <lb/>and when you see your matter <orig>blacke</orig>, <choice><orig>rejoyce</orig><reg>rejoice</reg></choice>, because it is the <orig>begining</orig> of<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>the <orig>worke</orig>: And, when it is first <orig>blacke</orig>, <orig>wee</orig> say it is the key of the <orig>worke</orig>,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>because it is not effected without <orig>blacknesse</orig>, as the Rosary <orig>hath</orig> it, with Arnold,
                        <lb/>and the Speculum: when you are operating, <orig>endeavour</orig> to <choice><orig>obtaine</orig><reg>obtain</reg></choice> first a<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>blacke</orig> <orig>colour</orig>, and then will you be <orig>certaine</orig> that you putrefy, and process
                        <lb/>the right way. And a little after: that <orig>blacknesse</orig> is called earth, which is made
                        <lb/>by light decoction <choice><orig>soe</orig><reg>so</reg></choice> often repeated, till <orig>blacknesse</orig> be most eminent. For<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>this reason say the same, that <orig>Saturne</orig> <choice><orig>possesseth</orig><reg>possesses</reg></choice> the earth, Mercury water,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Jupiter <orig>aire</orig>, Sol fire. <orig>Saturne</orig> therefore is <orig>blacknesse</orig>, the discoverer of truth,
                        <lb/>who <choice><orig>followes</orig><reg>follows</reg></choice> a stone instead of Jupiter. For <orig>blacknesse</orig>, that is, a <orig>darke</orig> cloud
                        <lb/>covers the stone as first, that is cannot be seen: Therefore <orig>sayth</orig> Morienes<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>every body without a <orig>soule</orig> is <orig>darke</orig> and obscure: And Hermes: Take his head<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>dissolve it with the Sharpest vinegar, or the vine of children, till it be made<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>darke</orig>: This being performed <orig>hee</orig> lines in putrefaction, and the <orig>darke</orig> clouds which
                        <lb/>were upon him, and in his body, before <orig>hee</orig> <choice><orig>dyed</orig><reg>died</reg></choice>, are returned. This stone is<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>againe</orig> disgorged by <orig>Saturne</orig>, when it becomes white, and then is it <choice><orig>sett</orig><reg>set</reg></choice> upon<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>the top of Helicon for a monument to men, as Hesiod writes: for <orig>whitenesse</orig> is
                        <lb/>really comprehended under <orig>blacknesse</orig>, which is <orig>drawne</orig> out of its <choice><orig>bowells</orig><reg>bowels</reg></choice>, that
                        <lb/>out of the <orig>stomacke</orig> of <orig>Saturne</orig>. therefore <orig>sayth</orig> Democritus; putrify <orig>Tinne</orig>
                        <lb/>with a peculiar ablution, draw its <orig>blacknesse</orig> and obscurity from it, and the
                        <lb/><orig>whitenesse</orig> of it will appear. And in Turba it is <orig>sayd</orig>: <orig>Joyne</orig> the dry with
                        <lb/>the moist, that is, the <orig>blacke</orig> earth with its water, and coct, till it be whitened.
                        <lb/>This Arnold in Novum lumen chapt. 4. excellently declares, saying; That<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>moisture therefore which caused <orig>blacknesse</orig> in decoction, <choice><orig>Shews</orig><reg>Shows</reg></choice> <orig>itselfe</orig> to be<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><choice><orig>dryed</orig><reg>dried</reg></choice>, when the white <orig>colour</orig> begins to appear. And a little after: And<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>my Master <orig>sayd</orig> to <orig>mee</orig>, that that brunity ascended, because the <orig>whitenesse</orig>
                        
                        
                        <pb n="43"/><fw>Discourse 12.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                        <lb/>was <orig>drawne</orig> out of the belly of its <orig>blacknesse</orig>, as is <orig>sayd</orig> in Turba: For when<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>you see it <orig>blacke</orig> know that the <orig>whitenesse</orig> of it is hidden in the <orig>bowells</orig> of the
                        <lb/><orig>blacknesse</orig> first appearing: As the Same <orig>blacknesse</orig> is called <orig>Saturne</orig>, <choice><orig>soe</orig><reg>so</reg></choice> <orig>allso</orig><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Lead: Thereupon <orig>sayth</orig> Agadimon in Turba: Coct your <orig>brasse</orig>, till the <orig>blacknesse</orig> come forth,
                        <lb/>which they call money, and mix the matters of your art, and you will find <orig>blacknesse</orig><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>presently, which is the Philosophers lead, of which they have treated much in their<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>books: Hitherto relates the saying of Emigamy, that the Splendor of <orig>Saturne</orig> ascending
                        <lb/>into the <orig>aire</orig> appears <orig>noe</orig> otherwise than darkened. And of Plato in the Rosary; The
                        <lb/>first way of governing <orig>Saturne</orig> is to putrefy and put it upon Sol: by which it is evident<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>that the sense of the Philosophers, speaking of <orig>Saturne</orig>, is <orig>farre</orig> different from the
                        <lb/><orig>coḿon</orig> acceptation. This <orig>Saturne</orig> generates Jupiter, that is, an obscure <orig>whitenesse</orig>, Jupiter
                        <lb/>of Latona Diana, that is perfect <orig>whitenesse</orig>, and Apollo, that is, <orig>rednesse</orig>; and this is
                        <lb/>the successive mutation of all perfect <orig>colours</orig>: This Stone cast out by <orig>Saturne</orig> is
                        <lb/>reported to be placed at the top of the mountaine as a monument to men, which
                        <lb/>is a thing most true<pc>. . . . . . . . . . . .</pc>
                    </ab>   
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

