<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="emblem" n="e33"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
                <pb n="104"/><!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                
                
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>
                        <lb/><orig>Embleme</orig> 33. of the Secrets of Nature.
                        <lb/>The Hermaphrodite lying like a dead man in <orig>darknesse</orig>, wants fire.
                    </head>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
                    <head><orig>Epigramme</orig> 33.</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>See here the cold and dry Hermaphrodite,</l>
                        <l>Appears as <choice><orig>dismall</orig><reg>dismal</reg></choice> as a ghost by night:</l>
                        <l>Fire is the thing <orig>hee</orig> wants, if that you give,</l>
                        <l>His Spirits feeling warmth will <orig>soone</orig> revive.</l>
                        <l>The Stone's whole virtue in God Vulcan <orig>lyes</orig>,</l>
                        <l>Sulphurs in Sol, in Luna <choice><orig>Mercurye's</orig><reg>Mercury's</reg></choice>.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                
                
                <pb n="105"/> <!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Discourse 33.</head>
                    <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                        <lb/>It is one of the secrets of Nature, that in the cold winter <choice><orig>Froggs</orig><reg>Frogs</reg></choice> and<pc>-</pc><milestone unit="section" n="e03-01" /> <!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                        <lb/>Horse<c rend="double-hyphen">-</c>leeches <orig>lye</orig> as it were dead under water, and in the Spring new<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>heat of the <orig>Sunne</orig> operating recover sense and motion, or <orig>performe</orig><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>the actions of a sensitive life: But if they be found in the waters<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>in the winter time, and brought into the <orig>aire</orig> or a <orig>warme</orig> house, they
                        <lb/>presently begin to move themselves, as in the Summer: From whence
                        <lb/>it appears, that they want nothing but <orig>externall</orig> heat, to excite the
                        <lb/><orig>naturall</orig> <orig>internall</orig> heat, and bring it to action: After the same man
                        <lb break="no"/>ner <orig>doe</orig> the Philosophers <orig>speake</orig> of their Hermaphrodite, who, if <orig>hee</orig>
                        <lb/>appears dead lying in <orig>darkenesse</orig>, requires the heat of fire: Now <orig>hee</orig><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>is <orig>sayd</orig> to <orig>lye</orig> in <orig>darkenesse</orig>, being left in a <orig>darke</orig> and most cold win
                        <lb break="no"/>ters night, that is, remaining in <orig>blacknesse</orig>, which is a <orig>signe</orig> of <orig>coldnesse</orig>,
                        <lb/>from which <orig>hee</orig> ought to be brought to <orig>whitenesse</orig> by a greater intension
                        <lb/>of fire, and by yet a greater, to <orig>rednesse</orig>: For, as Bodillus in Turba <orig>sayth</orig>,
                        <lb/>nothing is generated without heat, and a bath of vehement heat <choice><orig>causeth</orig><reg>causes</reg></choice><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>a body to perish, if it be cold it drives it away, but if it be temperate, it
                        <lb/>becomes <orig>agreable</orig> and pleasant to the body. Bonellus in the same <orig>sayth</orig>,
                        <lb/>All things that live <orig>doe</orig> <orig>allso</orig> (God <orig>soe</orig> pleasing) <orig>dye</orig>: that nature there
                        <lb break="no"/>fore, which is <choice><orig>depriv'd</orig><reg>deprived</reg></choice> of moisture, being <choice><orig>exposd</orig><reg>exposed</reg></choice> by night, seems like
                        <lb/>a dead man, and then that nature requires fire, till the body and Spi
                        <lb break="no"/>rit of it be turned into earth, and then it becomes dust like to a dead
                        <lb/>man in his <choice><orig>tombe</orig><reg>tomb</reg></choice>: these things being accomplished God restores a Spirit
                        <lb/>and <orig>Soule</orig> to it, and all infirmity being taken away our nature is com
                        <lb break="no"/>forted and amended: It is therefore requisite to <orig>burne</orig> that matter without
                        <lb/>fear Ct: Fire therefore, which <orig>destroyes</orig> all other things, <choice><orig>repaires</orig><reg>repairs</reg></choice> this, that
                        <lb/>which <orig>yeilds</orig> death to others gives life to this. One <orig>onely</orig> <choice><orig>Phænix</orig><reg>Phoenix</reg></choice> there is,
                        <lb/>which is restored by fire, which is renewed by flames, and revives out of
                        <lb/>ashes, and this being <orig>knowne</orig> to the Philosophers <orig>onely</orig> is burnt and
                        <lb/>restored to life, whatsoever other men <choice><orig>dreame</orig><reg>dream</reg></choice> of a bird, I know not<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>what, that <choice><orig>flyeth</orig><reg>flies</reg></choice>, residing <orig>noe</orig> where, nor seen, but as a fable. The
                        <lb/>Hermaphrodite, of which the Philosophers <orig>speake</orig>, is of a <orig>mixd</orig> na
                        <lb break="no"/>ture, male and female, whereof one <choice><orig>passeth</orig><reg>passes</reg></choice> into another by the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>operation of heat, for the female is converted into a male, which<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>ought not to seem <orig>soe</orig> strange in the Philosophers <orig>worke</orig>, it being<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>found, if <orig>wee</orig> may <orig>beleive</orig> <choice><orig>historyes</orig><reg>histories</reg></choice>, that many men have <orig>allso</orig><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><choice><orig>changd</orig><reg>changed</reg></choice> their sex: The <orig>Poetts</orig> make mention of Ceneus, Iphis, and
                        <lb/>Tiresias, as Pontanus in the <orig>Starrs</orig>.
                        <lb/>Pæniteat generis tamen et se Cenea malint,
                        <lb/>Aut in fæmineam penitus transire figuram: And Ausonius:
                        <lb/>Mæret in antiquam Ceneus revocata figuram.
                        <lb/><orig>Soe</orig> in the Consulship of Licinius Crassus, and Caius Cassius Longinus
                        
                        
                        
                        <pb n="106"/><fw>Discourse 33.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                        <lb/>at Cassinum a boy was made of a Virgin: And Licinius Mutianus in Pli
                        <lb break="no"/>ny relates, that <orig>hee</orig> had seen one Aristotles at Argos, called <orig>allso</orig> by the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>name of Aristotle, who was <choice><orig>marryd</orig><reg>married</reg></choice>, and soone after discovered a beard<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>and virility, and <choice><orig>marryd</orig><reg>married</reg></choice> a wife: Pliny <orig>himselfe</orig> <orig>sayth</orig> that in Africa
                        <lb/><orig>hee</orig> saw Lucius Cossicius a Citizen of Tisdritane <choice><orig>chang'd</orig><reg>changed</reg></choice> into a woman
                        <lb/>on the day of <choice><orig>mariage</orig><reg>marriage</reg></choice>: <orig>certaine</orig> it is that these things are true, and<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>might be proved by many other examples, if need were: but the <choice><orig>geni
                        <lb break="no"/>tall</orig><reg>genital</reg></choice> or virile parts are thrust out of the body by the <choice><orig>encrease</orig><reg>increase</reg></choice> of heat:
                        <lb/>For a woman being much colder than a man, and having inwardly<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>those things absconded, which a man <orig>hath</orig> outwardly, as Physicians<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>say, hereupon Nature being dubious, whether <orig>Shee</orig> Should generate a<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>man or a woman, <orig>hath</orig> <choice><orig>expressd</orig><reg>expressed</reg></choice> a woman outwardly, though inwardly<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>shee</orig> <choice><orig>conceivd</orig><reg>conceived</reg></choice> a man: for which reason heat and motion increasing<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>through age the hidden parts broke forth, and <choice><orig>shewd</orig><reg>showed</reg></choice> themselves visibly
                        <lb/>to all men: After the same manner with the Philosophers the woman is
                        <lb/><choice><orig>turnd</orig><reg>turned</reg></choice> into a man heat being increased, that is, the Hermaphrodite <choice><orig>loo
                        <lb break="no"/>seth</orig><reg>looses</reg></choice> the female sex, and becomes a man stout and grave, having<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>nothing in him of effeminacy or levity. <orig>Soe</orig> <orig>wee</orig> some time since<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>saw a noble youth an Hermaphrodite changed or rather promoted (by
                        <lb/>the industry of the <choice><orig>Chirurgicall</orig><reg>Surgical</reg></choice> art <orig>performd</orig> by that most famous
                        <lb/>Physician Caspius Tagliacolius of Bononia) into a perfect man, fit (as
                        <lb/>was desired) for the generating of an offspring, a new hole being made
                        <lb/>through the yard, which was wanting there, and the lower as appertai
                        <lb break="no"/>ning to the woman being <orig>stopd</orig> up. The Philosophers are not without
                        <lb/>all these <orig>manuall</orig> operations: for when the <orig>coldnesse</orig> and <choice><orig>moistnesse</orig><reg>moistness</reg></choice> of<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Luna appears, that they call the woman, when the heat and siccity of
                        <lb/>Sol, the man; <add>when</add> all those four <orig>qualityes</orig> together, <del>being</del> their Rebis or Her
                        <lb break="no"/>maphrodite; And thus conversion of the woman may easily be made,
                        <lb/>that is, the mutation of <orig>coldnesse</orig> and <choice><orig>moistnesse</orig><reg>moistness</reg></choice>, into the man, which is
                        <lb/>done by the sole heat of fire, as <orig>hath</orig> been <orig>sayd</orig>; for heat sequesters,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>and separates the <orig>superfluityes</orig> of moistures, and will establish the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>idea of <orig>itselfe</orig> in the <orig>Philosophicall</orig> subject, which is the tincture<pc>. .</pc>
                    </ab>   
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
