<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="emblem" n="e43"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
                <pb n="134"/><!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                
                
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>
                        <lb/>Embleme 43. Of the Secrets of Nature.
                        <lb/>Give ear to the Vultur's words, which are noewise false.
                    </head>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Epigramme 43.</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>The Vultur on the mountaine stands in sight,</l>
                        <l>Himselfe proclaiming daily, blacke, and white,</l>
                        <l>Citrine, and red; nor false: The Raven is</l>
                        <l>The same, which without wings by nature flyes</l>
                        <l>In dismall darkenesse, and in glorious light,</l>
                        <l>For either will to th' art conduct you right.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                
                
                <pb n="135"/> <!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Discourse 43.</head>
                    <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                        <lb/>Wee daily in many places hear birds prattling or imitating the voyce<milestone unit="section" n="e03-01" /> <!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                        <lb/>of man, such as Parrotts, Ravens, Dawes, and Pyes. Soe Pliny writes<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>that, at the time wherein hee published his history, Agrippina the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>wife of Claudius Cæsar had a thrush, imitating the speech of men.<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>The young Cæsars had allso a Starling and Nightingales accustomed to
                        <lb/>the Greeke and Latine tongue, and daily speaking new things, with<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>a long forme of words allso. But such birds now frequently happening
                        <lb/>they are thought lesse worthy of admiration, for all birds endu'd<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>with a broad tongue may by use and custome be brought to speake
                        <lb/>and babble. But that Vultur, which the Philosophers make mention
                        <lb/>of, did not learne words, if any hee utters, by use, but his nature tacit
                        <lb break="no"/>ly expresseth them. The Philosophers doe indeed say, that hee<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>continually cryes out, and with a loud Voyce pronounceth, who and
                        <lb/>what hee is, wherein hee imitates great Princes, who in the begining
                        <lb/>of their intimations will allwayes make their titles and inheritances<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>knowne, not in token of any pride, but for other reasons, that they<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>allso themselves may know, what principalityes they governe, or<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>right of inheritance they prætend to: Soe it is very materiall to<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>know, what colours, as ensigns of armes and titles, the Philosophi
                        <lb break="no"/>call bird is adornd with, and wherein hee excells all others. I, Sayth hee,
                        <lb/>as Rosarius hath it from Hermes, am the blacke of white, and the ci
                        <lb break="no"/>trine of red, and certainly I speake truth and lye not. Hee affirmes
                        <lb/>himselfe blacke, white, citrine, and red, and such hee really is, for<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>though hee doth not as yet actually possesse the last colours, yet hee
                        <lb/>expects the inheritance of them: Hereupon Sayth Rosinus in his booke
                        <lb/>of divine interpretations; Take the Stone, which is blacke, white,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>red, citrine, that admirable bird, which flyes without wings in the
                        <lb/>darknesse of the night, and clearnesse of the day: For coloration<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>ariseth from the bitternesse which is in his throat, but mere water<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>proceeds from his blood, as Alexander sayd. Take (My Sonne) the
                        <lb/>Stone of four colours. The Philosophers books doe abundantly de
                        <lb break="no"/>clare and insinuate that the Stone hath all these colours, which
                        <lb/>are principall, in a successive order. But why the Philosophicall
                        <lb/>subject is calld a Vultur, there is reason to be alleadged. Of Vulturs<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>the blacke are of most esteem, they are rapacious, but fly Slowly, be
                        <lb break="no"/>cause of the bignesse of body. They say that this bird conceives<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>without the seed of the males, and generates without coition, and
                        <lb/>that their offspring doe arrive to a great age even to a hundred<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>years. Their nests they build in high rocks, noe man hath attained
                        <lb/>to them. Two chickens are for the most part seen: They are helpe
                        <lb break="no"/>full and commodious agaynst Serpents. They are offended and<pc>-</pc>
                        
                        
                        
                        <pb n="136"/><fw>Discourse 43.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                        <lb/>perplexed with the East wind. When they begin to lay eggs, they<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>bring a thing out of the Indyes, which is as a nutt, having within a<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>thing that may be moved, and forthwith yeild a sound, which when
                        <lb/>they have applyed to them, they produce many young chickens,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>but one onely remayns, which is calld Immusulus. Hermodorus Fon
                        <lb break="no"/>ticus in Cælius is a wittnesse, that Vulturs of all animalls are the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>most innocent, because they doe not at all meddle with any of those
                        <lb/>things which men sow, plant, and breed. Moreover they kill noe<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>animalls. They allso abstaine from birds though dead by a certaine
                        <lb/>instinct of affinity: For this cause they were best esteemd in divina
                        <lb break="no"/>tions, as the originalls of the Citty of Rome declare. The Philoso
                        <lb break="no"/>phicall bird expressing allmost all these propertyes of Vulturs, is
                        <lb/>therefore by Hermes and others not undeservedly called Vultur, which
                        <lb/>is allso slow in flight, and blacke of colour; It conceives by itselfe:
                        <lb/>For thus sayth Rosarius about the end; And it is the Dragon, which
                        <lb/>wedds itselfe, and impregnats itselfe, and brings forth in its owne
                        <lb/>season Ct. And Rosinus to Sarratant: And that is the Serpent, ad
                        <lb break="no"/>ministring pleasure to itselfe, impregnating itselfe, and bringing
                        <lb/>forth in one day, Ct. It lives and endures a very long time, and<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>multiplyes itselfe. For that which Virgill writes of the bird calld
                        <lb/>a Phænix, is as proper to this, because it is the same.
                        <lb/>Alipedem Cervum Corvus ter vincit, at illum
                        <lb/>Multiplicat novies Phænix reparabilis abes.
                        <lb/>Three ages of a Hart the Raven lives,
                        <lb/>Which the rare Phænix nine times 'ore survives.
                        <lb/>It is very difficult to climbe this birds nest: It fights with the Mercuriall
                        <lb/>serpent, and overcomes it, that is, Sol with Luna. It is conceived by<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>the wind, and carryed in its belly, and bred in the aire. The<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Stone Ælites, containing a little stone sounding within <add>it</add> is by many
                        <lb/>men called Totium. One onely Immusulus is found in the Philoso
                        <lb break="no"/>phers nest. The Philosophicke bird is allso most innocent, because
                        <lb/>it hurts noe body, it is beneficiall to all that know it, and most ex
                        <lb break="no"/>cellent in divinations. But why doth it make its nest on a Mountaine,
                        <lb/>and sitting soe cry out? Rosinus answers according to Rasis, who sayth.
                        <lb/>Behold the most high mountains, which are both on the right and
                        <lb/>left, and climbe up thither: There is our Stone found, and in another
                        <lb/>mountaine, which produceth all sorts of Painter colours, and Spirits<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>or Species, there likewise it is: Morienus: Climbe up the high mountains,
                        <lb/>planted wih trees, because there is our stone found, and hidden: And Hermes:
                        <lb/>Take yee the blessed Stone, breake it to peices, and wash the red stone, from
                        <lb/>which is extracted that which is found in mountains, and especially sometimes in old Sinks.
                    </ab>   
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>