<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="emblem" n="e16"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
                <pb n="53"/><!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                
                
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>
                        <lb/>Embleme 16. Of the Secrets of Nature.
                        <lb/>One Lyon hath wings, the other none.
                    </head>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Epigramme 16.</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>The Lyon prince of beasts in might and sway</l>
                        <l>Fights without fear, and scornes to runne away:</l>
                        <l>Give him a Spouse with wings of his owne race,</l>
                        <l>To mount him with herselfe from place to place;</l>
                        <l>But hee immoved stands, and nulls her force,</l>
                        <l>By Embleme to demonstrate Natures course.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                
                
                <pb n="54"/> <!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Discourse 16.</head>
                    <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                        <lb/>It is a thing knowne by experience that a Lyon excells other animalls not<milestone unit="section" n="e03-01" /> <!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                        <lb/>soe much in bignesse and strength of body, as generosity: if hee be seen in
                        <lb/>hunting, being ashamd to runne away, hee releaseth himselfe by degrees,
                        <lb/>if hee be oppressd by a multitude: being removed from the view of the
                        <lb/>hunters, hee makes hast away, thinking it a dishonour to be excusd by ab
                        <lb break="no"/>sconding: hee desires a wood in flight, which hee useth, when anything
                        <lb/>pursues: his bones are solid and not at all empty, which are sayd to be
                        <lb/>soe hard, that being shakd together they yeild fire as out of a sheet and
                        <lb/>flint. Hee fears fire above all things. Hee seems to derive his substance
                        <lb/>from the nature of the sunne, for in force and heat hee excells other
                        <lb/>animalls, as the Sunne doth the Starrs: Besides hee is allways beheld with
                        <lb/>fiery and open eyes, as the Sunne beholds the earth with an open and
                        <lb/>fiery eye: a Lionesse fighting for her whelps fixeth her eyes upon the
                        <lb/>ground, that Shee may not be afrayd of the hunters Staffs and Spears.
                        <lb/>where a Lyon perceives the coition of a Leopard, hee takes revenge
                        <lb/>upon the Lionesse for adultery, and infeicts severe punnishment;
                        <lb/>The Lionesse therefore washeth away the offence and scent in a river,
                        <lb/>or being conscious of the trespasse doth allso accompany the adulterer
                        <lb/>flying for fear of the make: Which wonderfull nature of this beast the
                        <lb/>Philosophers contemplating, have produced severall allegoryes of the
                        <lb/>Lyon, as it were hieroglyphicall writings testifying of their secret
                        <lb/>worke, observing the Lyon to be a constant, firme animall, without
                        <lb/>deceipt and suspicion, they assimilated the better part of their Phi
                        <lb break="no"/>losophicall composition to him: for as hee flyes not, soe neither this:
                        <lb/>hee with solid bones, soe this fixed and not to be overcome: and as
                        <lb/>the Lionesse is not allways innocent and free from adultery, soe
                        <lb/>is neither Luna nor Mercury without some blemish, but is joyned
                        <lb/>by the ignorant sometimes to this, sometimes to that matter, where
                        <lb break="no"/>by an adulterous conjunction of things discrepant and different in
                        <lb/>nature rather than true matrimony is established: for the products
                        <lb/>of a Leopard and Lionesse have noe specious and comely mains
                        <lb/>about the necke and Shoulders; with which ensigne those generated
                        <lb/>by the Lyon are alone adorned. The Philosophicall Lionesse must
                        <lb/>therefore be joyned to her proper mate or male, and a genuine
                        <lb/>and generous whelp will from theme Spring, which may easily
                        <lb/>be knowne by his paw. But the Lionesse must not be any or
                        <lb/>what you pledge, but winged, which may be able to fight and
                        <lb/>contest with the Lyon, depending upon the Swiftnesse of her
                        <lb/>plumes, lest (to witt) Shee Should be oppressed by his extraordi
                        <lb break="no"/>nary wrath, but to thinke upon escape, if at any time hee fall
                        <lb/>into fury without cause, for hee when hee stops her flying
                        
                        
                        
                        <pb n="55"/><fw>Discourse 16.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                        <lb/>is incited with greater love toward her, freindship being made after discord.
                        <lb/>But you will say who ever saw a Lionesse with wings, or what can the plumes
                        <lb/>of a Lionesse avayle? There is a deep valley near the mountaine Cythaeren,
                        <lb/>in which are seen none but flying Lionesse, and at the top of the same
                        <lb/>mountaine resorts a red Lyon of that kind, which Hercules killed. The
                        <lb/>Lyon therefore must be taken, and brought into the valley, and forthwith
                        <lb/>coupled to the winged Lionesse: Shee allso will easily suffer herselfe to
                        <lb/>be overcome, as like by like: afterwards they must be both advanced
                        <lb/>out of the sayd valley to the top of the mountaine, and henceforth they
                        <lb/>will never desert one another, but allwayes remaine together in inviolable
                        <lb/>amity: The taking of Lyons. I confesse, is not easy, but obnoxious to many
                        <lb/>dangers, neverthelesse it must be attempted: a Lyon feeds not with the
                        <lb/>Lionesse, but strayes apart, as story relates, therefore they are to be found and
                        <lb/>hunted severally: But if the Lyons whelps be obtaind in their infancy, when
                        <lb/>they first begin to goe, which is at two moneths age, and be joyned, as afore
                        <lb break="no"/>sayd, being come to good growth and stature, the thing will be free from
                        <lb/>any danger. Moreover they breed in the Spring time, which must be well
                        <lb/>observed: but Lyons after whelping using crosse and winding wayes, to
                        <lb/>praevent the discovery of their denne, therefore must they be sought and
                        <lb/>their whelps taken away very great diligence and care
                        
                    </ab>   
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

