<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="emblem" n="e01"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
                <pb n="8"/><!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                
                
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>
                        <lb/>the first Embleme. Of the Secrets of Nature.
                        <lb/><unclear reason="illegible">Wine</unclear> carres him in his belly
                        
                    </head>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>the first Epigramme.</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>If Boreas <unclear reason="illegible">onto</unclear> expand his windy wombe,</l>
                        <l>That th' Infant in the world alive may come,</l>
                        <l>His prowesse will the Heroes all outlive</l>
                        <l>In art, in hand, in mind, and body too.</l>
                        <l>Thinke him noe Caeso, nor abortive brood,</l>
                        <l>Nor yet Agrippa, for his starre was good.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                
                
                <pb n="9"/> <!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Discourse 1.</head>
                    <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                        <lb/><milestone unit="section" n="e01-01" />Hermes the most industrious inquisitor into every naturall secret doth<!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                        <lb/>in his Smaragdine table elegantly, though concisely, describe the naturalle
                        <lb/>worke, where amongst other things hee sayth: the wind carrys him in his
                        <lb/>belly: as if hee should say, Hee, whose father is Sol, and mother Luna,
                        <lb/>must, before hee can be brought to light, be carryed by windy fumes, even
                        <lb/>as a bird is caryed by the aire, when it flyes: now from fumes or winds, (which
                        <lb/>are nothing els but aire moves) coagulated is produced water, from which mixed
                        <lb/>with earth doe proceed all mineralls and metalls: yea these very things are
                        <lb/>determined to consist and be imediately coagulates of fumes: whether
                        <lb/>therefore it be ascribed to water or fume, the thing is the same, because
                        <lb/>they are both the matter of wind: the same may be sayd of mineralls
                        <lb/>and metalls, though more remotely: now the question is, who hee is, what
                        <lb/>ought to be carryd by wind! I answer, Chymically, it is Sulphur, which is
                        <lb/>carryd in Argent vive, as Lully in his booke, Chapt 32 attest, and alle the <note place="margin">Lully there. <lb/>The wind carryd <lb/>him in his belly, that <lb/>is, Sulphur is carryd <lb/>in <!-- need to insert chymical symbol somehow -->. and Chap. 47 <lb/>The Stone is fire <lb/>carryd in the belly <lb/>of aire</note>
                        <lb/>rest: physically, it is an infant, which ought in a little time to be borne into
                        <lb/>the world: I say allso Arithmetically, that it is the root of a Cube; Musically,
                        <lb/>that it is the Disdiapason; Geometrically, that it is a punctum the begining
                        <lb/>of a running line; Astronomically, the center of the planets, Saturne,
                        <lb/>Jupiter, and Mars: though these be different subjects, yet if they be
                        <lb/>well compard together, they will easily demonstrate the offspring of wind,
                        <lb/>which must be left to everymans industry more or lesse. But I indigitate
                        <lb/>the matter more plainly thus: every Mercury is compounded of fumes, 
                        <lb/>that is, of water elevating earth with it into an airy rarity, and of earth
                        <lb/>forcing aire to returne into a watry earth or earthy water: for the Ele
                        <lb break="no"/>ments being alltogether in it, and mixes, and subdued and reduced together
                        <lb/>into a viscous nature, they doe not easily recede one from the other; but <!-- numbers above several words in next line -->
                        <lb/>either the volatile doe follow above, or remayne below with the fixes, the
                        <lb/>first whereof is evident in comon Mercury, the other in the philosophicall
                        <lb/>and fixes metalls: in these the fixes Elements doe predominate the volatile,
                        <lb/>in that the volatile oversway the fixes: nor indeed is it without reason, that 
                        <lb/>Mercury is calld and reputed the mossenger, interpreter, and as it were the
                        <lb/>running intermediate minister of the other Gods, with wings fitted to his
                        <lb/>head and feet: for hee is windy, and flyes through the aire as wind itselfe,
                        <lb/>as is comonly <!-- is is putting something consistly above the second o in comon? -->and really confirmes to the damage of many men; but car=
                        <lb break="no"/>rying a white wand girt with two Serpents crossewise, which can draw soules
                        <lb/>out of bodyes, and bring them backe againe, and doe many such contrary
                        <lb/>things, hee exquisitely repraesents the philosophicall Mercury. Mercury there
                        <lb break="no"/>fore is wind, which takes Sulphur or Dionysius, or, if you had rasher, Ascu
                        <lb break="no"/>lapius, being yet an imperfect Embryo, out of the mothers belly, or even out
                        <lb/>of the ashes of the mothers body burned, and carryes it thither, where it
                        <lb/>may be matured; and the Embryo is Sulphur, which is infused into
                        <lb/>the belly of Boreas by the caelestialle Sunne, that hee may bring it
                        <lb/>forth being matured, who in the compleat time of his cariage produceth
                        <lb/>twins, one with white haire, called Calais, the other with red, named
                        <lb/>Zethe: these Sonns of Boreas were (as Orphens the Chymicall poet writes)
                        
                        
                        <pb n="10"/><fw>Discourse 1.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                        <lb/>with Jason among the Argonauts to carry away the golden fleece from Col
                        <lb break="no"/>chos: and phineus the blind prophet, infested by the Harpyes, could not be
                        <lb/>freed, but by the sayd Sonns of Boreas, for which benefitt obtained from
                        <lb/>them, hee, being gratefull, declare the whole manner of the way to the
                        <lb/>Argonauts: But the Harpyes are noe other, than corrupting Sulphur, which
                        <lb/>is driven away by the Sonns of Boreas, having attaind to full age, and of a
                        <lb/>thing imperfect or molested with noxious birds is made perfect, not sub
                        <lb break="no"/>ject to that evile, which then shews to Jason the physician the way to
                        <lb/>obtaine the golden fleece. these winds our countryman Basill amongst
                        <lb/>others allso lakes notice of, and plainly sayth: <subst><del><unclear reason="illegible">The</unclear></del><add>A double</add></subst>wind ought to <subst><del>come</del><add>arise</add></subst>
                        <lb/><del>that</del>called Vulturnus, and <subst><del>after that one</del><add>then a single wind</add></subst>, called Notus, which <subs><del>must</del><add>will</add></subs>blow
                        <lb/>from the East and South impetuously, whose motion coasing, soe as wa
                        <lb break="no"/>ter to be made of aire, you <subst><del>may</del><add>will</add></subst>confidently believe, that a corporall
                        <lb/>thing will be made of a spirituall. And Ripley gate 8. sayth, that
                        <lb/>our Infant ought to be borne againe in aire, that is, in the belly of
                        <lb/>wind: sayth scala philosophorum, degree 6. after the same sense thus:
                        <lb/>You must know that the Sonne of the wife is borne in the aire: and
                        <lb/>degree 8: Airy spirits asconding together into the aire doe love <subst><del>them</del><add>one</add></subst>
                        <lb/><subst><del>selves</del><add>another</add></subst>, as Hermes sayth, the wind carrye him in its belly: because
                        <lb/>the generation of our Sonne is made in the aire, and being borne
                        <lb/>in the aire is borne wisely: for hee ascends from earth to heaven, and
                        <lb/>againe descends to earth acquiring both the superiour and inferiour
                        <lb/>virtue.
                        
                        <lb />
                        <pc>- - - - - </pc>
                        
                    </ab>   
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

