<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="emblem" n="e39"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
                <pb n="122"/><!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                
                
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>
                        <lb/><orig>Embleme</orig> 39. Of the Secrets of Nature.
                        <lb/><orig>Œdipus</orig> having overcome <orig>Sphynx</orig>, and <orig>Killd</orig> his father Laius,
                        <lb/><orig>marryed</orig> his Mother Jocasta.
                    </head>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
                    <head><orig>Epigramme</orig> 39.</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l><orig>Sphynx</orig> with her riddles did the Thebans dread,</l>
                        <l>But <orig>subtill</orig> <orig>Œdipus</orig> her wiles <choice><orig>betrayd</orig><reg>betrayed</reg></choice>:</l>
                        <l>The <orig>quæstion</orig> was, who in the morning might</l>
                        <l>Have four feet, two at noon, and three at night.</l>
                        <l><orig>Unknowne</orig> his father <orig>hee</orig> deprives of life</l>
                        <l>And his <orig>owne</orig> mother takes to be his wife</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                
                
                <pb n="123"/> <!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Discourse 39.</head>
                    <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                        <lb/>Bacasser a Philosopher in Turba <orig>sayth</orig>, that which you <orig>seeke</orig> for is of <orig>noe</orig> small<milestone unit="section" n="e03-01" /> <!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                        <lb/>value, for you <orig>seeke</orig> the greatest treasure, and most excellent gift of God.<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>And <orig>learne</orig>, O <choice><orig>yee</orig><reg>ye</reg></choice> students, that which the Philosophers have long since inti
                        <lb break="no"/>mated, saying, The truth is not discerned but by <orig>errour</orig>, and nothing begets<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>more <orig>greife</orig> to the heart, than <orig>errour</orig> in this art and <orig>worke</orig>: For when a man
                        <lb/>thinks <orig>hee</orig> <orig>hath</orig> done, <orig>hath</orig> a world, <orig>hee</orig> will find nothing in his<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>hands. these same things the ancient Philosophers were <choice><orig>pleasd</orig><reg>pleased</reg></choice>
                        <lb/>to signify, propounding a <orig>Sphynx</orig> as if <orig>shee</orig> denoted the obscu
                        <lb break="no"/>rity and meanders of art. For this reason the <orig>Ægyptians</orig>, in their
                        <lb/>sacred Isiaci, which were <choice><orig>celebratted</orig><reg>celebrated</reg></choice> in <orig>honour</orig> of Osiris, by mitred
                        <lb/><orig>Preists</orig>, with heads shaven, and all parts of the body <orig>cloathed</orig> with
                        <lb/>a white <orig>linnen</orig> garment <orig>downe</orig> to the ankles, that they might not
                        <lb/>be <orig>knowne</orig> or discovered to the <orig>coḿon</orig> people, erected a Statue of
                        <lb/>Silence, which was called Sigalion, in the entrance of the alter,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>the assistants being <orig>enjoyned</orig> to keep silence, and <orig>turne</orig> their<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>eyes to that image, and for the same cause they added the effi
                        <lb break="no"/>gies of <orig>Sphynxes</orig> at the corners of the altar, which did represent
                        <lb/>the <orig>mysticall</orig> knowledge of sacred things; as <seg rend="underline">Boissardus</seg> <orig>doth</orig> from
                        <lb/>ancient Authors demonstrate: For <orig>Sphynx</orig> is a <orig>certaine</orig> kind of Mon
                        <lb break="no"/>ster most obscure to the Thebans, propounding riddles, nor <orig>onely</orig> to<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>them, but as before to the <orig>Ægyptians</orig>, <orig>soe</orig> after all others to those that<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>aspire to art, and <choice><orig>watcheth</orig><reg>watches</reg></choice> in the Philosophers books as before the gates of
                        <lb/>Thebes; if any man can <orig>passe</orig> by the monster, <orig>hee</orig> suffers <orig>noe</orig> <orig>evill</orig> by
                        <lb/>him, but <orig>hee</orig> that through <choice><orig>præsumption</orig><reg>presumption</reg></choice> of mind or <orig>witt</orig> <orig>endeavours</orig> to<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>resolve his riddles, and cannot <orig>performe</orig>, acquires his <orig>owne</orig> destruction,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>that is, <orig>greife</orig> to the heart, and damage to his <orig>affaires</orig> by <orig>errour</orig> in this<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>worke</orig>. <orig>Hee</orig> that <orig>referrs</orig> such <orig>allegoryes</orig> to history, <orig>hath</orig> a <choice><orig>Mushrome</orig><reg>Mushroom</reg></choice> for<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>a head, and a Millon for a heart, as the <choice><orig>Comædian</orig><reg>Comedian</reg></choice> <orig>sayth</orig>, and <orig>knowes</orig> <orig>noe</orig>
                        <lb/>more than that <orig>hee</orig> deviates from the right way. Those things are too
                        <lb/>childish, and <orig>fitt</orig> for old wives, if they be taken literally, otherwise the
                        <lb/>signs and tokens of profound learning. Monstrous wild beasts are indeed
                        <lb/><orig>sayd</orig> to be in Africa by the name of <orig>Sphynxes</orig>, but here <orig>wee</orig> discourse not
                        <lb/>of them, though the <orig>originall</orig> and denomination of this fiction seems to<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>be derived from them. The Philosophers <orig>Sphynx</orig> understands and<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><choice><orig>useth</orig><reg>uses</reg></choice> <orig>humane</orig> speech, namely <choice><orig>greeke</orig><reg>greek</reg></choice>, as <orig>allso</orig> <choice><orig>propoundes</orig><reg>propounds</reg></choice> <orig>Subtill</orig> sen
                        <lb break="no"/>tences and <choice><orig>æmigmaticall</orig><reg>enigmatical</reg></choice> <orig>quæstions</orig>, in which appears a singular <choice><orig>Sharp
                        <lb break="no"/>nesse</orig><reg>Sharpness</reg></choice> of understanding and learning, not <orig>soe</orig> obvious to all other men,
                        <lb/>from which brutes are <orig>exceding</orig> distant. <orig>Hee</orig> that is conversant in<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>the Philosophers assertions will easily know them to be such: For<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>where one thing is <orig>sayd</orig>, and another thing <orig>signifyd</orig>, there <choice><orig>æqui
                        <lb break="no"/>vocation</orig><reg>equivocation</reg></choice> <choice><orig>begetts</orig><reg>begets</reg></choice> <orig>errour</orig>, which is not <orig>onely</orig> permitted, but <orig>allso</orig> <orig>enjoyned</orig>
                        
                        
                        
                        <pb n="124"/><fw>Discourse 39.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                        <lb/>to the Philosophers alone: The City of Thebes therefore being long<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>perplexed with the riddles of <orig>Sphynx</orig> at length came one <orig>Œdipus</orig>,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>who gave such responses to the <orig>quæstions</orig> offered, that <orig>Sphynx</orig> could
                        <lb/>not forbear throwing <orig>herselfe</orig> downe from a <orig>rocke</orig>. But who is this<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>Œdipus</orig>? The <orig>Sonne</orig> of the King of Thebes, who being <orig>borne</orig>, it be
                        <lb break="no"/>ing <choice><orig>prædicted</orig><reg>predicted</reg></choice> to his father by an oracle, that <orig>hee</orig> should be <orig>Slayne</orig>
                        <lb/>by his <orig>Sonne</orig>, <orig>hee</orig> <orig>coḿanded</orig> <orig>Œdipus</orig> to be <orig>killd</orig>, who being <choice><orig>hangd</orig><reg>hanged</reg></choice><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>upon a tree and left with a rope fastened <orig>crosse</orig> his feet, was relea
                        <lb break="no"/>sed by another country<c rend="double-hyphen">-</c>man, and brought up; <orig>Hee</orig> coming to mans
                        <lb/>estate had indeed <choice><orig>swelld</orig><reg>swelled</reg></choice> feet, but sufficiently declared a <orig>quicke</orig><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>witt</orig> above all men in unriddling this <choice><orig>ænigma</orig><reg>enigma</reg></choice> propounded by <orig>Sphynx</orig>.
                        <lb/>But Sphinx is reported to have had many riddles, though this the <orig>cheife</orig>,
                        <lb/>offered to <orig>Œdipus</orig>. What is that which in the morning <choice><orig>goeth</orig><reg>goes</reg></choice> upon <orig>foure</orig>
                        <lb/>feet, at <choice><orig>noone</orig><reg>noon</reg></choice> upon two, in the evening upon three? what was <orig>answerd</orig>
                        <lb/>by <orig>Œdipus</orig> is not <orig>knowne</orig>; but some interpret it to the age of man, who
                        <lb/>are deceived: For a Quadrangle or the four Elements of all things are
                        <lb/>first to be considered, from hence <orig>wee</orig> come to the hemisphere having
                        <lb/>two lines one <choice><orig>streight</orig><reg>straight</reg></choice> the other crooked, that is, while Luna, from hence
                        <lb/>to a Triangle, which consists of body, Spirit, and <orig>Soule</orig>, or Sol, Luna,
                        <lb/>and Mercury: Hereupon <orig>sayth</orig> Rhasis in his Epistle. The Stone is a Tri
                        <lb break="no"/>angle in being, a Quadrangle in quality. Hereto <orig>allso</orig> relates the one
                        <lb/>and <choice><orig>twentyeth</orig><reg>twentieth</reg></choice> <orig>embleme</orig>, and the exposition thereof. <orig>Œdipus</orig> moreover
                        <lb/>is notorious for parricide and incest, which are two the most detestable<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>vices, as can ever be thought of, but <orig>neverthelesse</orig> they promoted him to a
                        <lb/><orig>kingdome</orig>, otherwise due to him, <orig>hee</orig> having unawares killed his father<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>refusing to give way to him, and <orig>marryed</orig> the Queen, the wife of Laius,
                        <lb/>his <orig>owne</orig> mother. But this written not to be imitated by any man as
                        <lb/>history, or example, it being <orig>onely</orig> feigned and allegorically intro
                        <lb break="no"/>duced by the Philosophers to discover the secrets of their doctrine. For
                        <lb/>in this <orig>worke</orig> both happen; the first efficient, that is, the father, being
                        <lb/><orig>killd</orig> and destroyed by his effect, that is, the <orig>Sonne</orig>, and afterwards<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>the same effect <orig>joynd</orig> the second efficient to <orig>himselfe</orig>, till <orig>shee</orig> be
                        <lb break="no"/>come one with him, and <orig>soe</orig> the <orig>Sonne</orig> is coupled to his mother by<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>matrimony, and <orig>enjoyes</orig> his fathers <orig>kingdome</orig>, as it were by a triple<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>right, of <choice><orig>armes</orig><reg>arms</reg></choice>, <choice><orig>wedlocke</orig><reg>wedlock</reg></choice>, and succession. <orig>Hee</orig> <orig>hath</orig> <choice><orig>swelld</orig><reg>swelled</reg></choice> feet, because
                        <lb/><orig>hee</orig> cannot <orig>runne</orig>, and is as a bear, as <orig>hee</orig> <orig>containes</orig> the greatest se
                        <lb break="no"/>cret, or a toad, going with a slow pace; because it is fixed fixing<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>another, and not <orig>avoyding</orig> or fearing fire, which though a medium
                        <lb/>of mean repute the Philosophers can by <orig>noe</orig> means be without<pc>. .</pc>
                    </ab>   
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>