<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="emblem" n="e46"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
                <pb n="143"/><!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                
                
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>
                        <lb/><orig>Embleme</orig> 46. Of the Secrets of Nature.
                        <lb/>Two Eagles come together, one from the East, the other from the West.
                    </head>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
                    <head><orig>Epigramme</orig> 46.</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>Great Jove two Eagles out of Delphi sent</l>
                        <l>To <choice><orig>th'</orig><reg>the</reg></choice> East and Western parts, for this intent,</l>
                        <l>That <orig>hee</orig> the <orig>midle</orig> of the earth might find;</l>
                        <l>Which there returning, well <choice><orig>resolv'd</orig><reg>resolved</reg></choice> his mind.</l>
                        <l>But those two Eagles are two stones, which <choice><orig>hast</orig><reg>have</reg></choice></l>
                        <l>One from the East, the other from the West.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                
                
                <pb n="144"/> <!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Discourse 46.</head>
                    <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                        <lb/>Cicero in his <orig>booke</orig> of the nature of the Gods declares the most ancient<pc>-</pc><milestone unit="section" n="e03-01" /> <!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                        <lb/>Apollo to be the <orig>Sonne</orig> of Vulcan, and keeper of Athens: Which opinion,
                        <lb/>if it be, as it ought, <choice><orig>transferrd</orig><reg>transferred</reg></choice> to an Allegory, is indeed most true; because
                        <lb/>Vulcan <orig>produceth</orig> the <orig>Philosophicall</orig> Sol, which is Apollo. But it <orig>hath</orig><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>prævayld</orig>, that <orig>hee</orig> was <orig>borne</orig> of Jupiter; and that Latona having two
                        <lb/>children in her <orig>wombe</orig>, Apollo and Diana, which <orig>shee</orig> <choice><orig>conceivd</orig><reg>conceived</reg></choice> of Ju
                        <lb break="no"/>piter, Juno being jealous sent Python a Serpent of prodigious magni
                        <lb break="no"/>tude and malice, to persecute and perplex her being great with child.<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>The miserable woman after tedious <choice><orig>wandrings</orig><reg>wanderings</reg></choice> was at length brought
                        <lb/>by a <orig>Shipp</orig> to the Island Ortygia, to her sister Asteries, who therein
                        <lb/>reigned: And that Island, being <orig>allmost</orig> all overflowed with the Sea,
                        <lb/>gave place to Latona being in <orig>travell</orig>, whereupon it was called Delos,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>which before was <seg rend="superscript">11</seg> Aδηλος: There therefore being in <orig>labour</orig>, first came forth
                        <lb/>Diana, and <orig>shee</orig> did the office of a midwife to her mother <orig>labouring</orig><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>to bring forth her brother Apollo; From whence it came to <orig>passe</orig><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>that women going with Child did in the time of their <orig>labour</orig>
                        <lb/>invoke her deity, and <orig>calld</orig> her either Lucina or Ilithya, be
                        <lb break="no"/>cause <orig>shee</orig> <orig>shewd</orig> light to infants <orig>borne</orig> their eyes being opened:
                        <lb/>Apollo therefore being <orig>borne</orig> and <orig>growne</orig> up slew Python the tor
                        <lb break="no"/>menter of his mother with arrows, and <orig>killd</orig> the Cyclopes because<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>they made lightening for Jupiter to destroy his <orig>Sonne</orig> <choice><orig>Æsculapius</orig><reg>Esculapius</reg></choice>,
                        <lb/><orig>whome</orig> Jupiter condemned to hell blasted with lightening, because
                        <lb/><orig>hee</orig> had <choice><orig>restord</orig><reg>restored</reg></choice> Hippolytus to life being <orig>torne</orig> in <orig>peices</orig> by horses.
                        <lb/><orig>Wee</orig> have in many places demonstrated these things to be merely
                        <lb/><orig>Chymicall</orig>: For Latona, Cynthia, Apollo, and Python are requisites of
                        <lb/>the art, which have such a relation one to the other, as <orig>hath</orig> been
                        <lb/>declared; but these things being divulged in the writings of the most
                        <lb/>ancient <orig>Poetts</orig>, as <orig>Orphens</orig>, Linus, <choice><orig>Musæus</orig><reg>Musaeus</reg></choice>, Homer, Ct. have given the
                        <lb/>ignorant occasion to ascribe religion and veneration to Apollo: Here
                        <lb break="no"/>upon Apollo is in many places of Europe and Asia worshipped,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>and innumerable temples erected to him; And especially at Delphos
                        <lb/><orig>hee</orig> had a temple to be worshipped by ancient religion, wherein a great
                        <lb/>number of statues made of solid gold and silver or great weight<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>and artifice was reposited by Kings and Princes, with other most
                        <lb/><orig>pretious</orig> gifts, which were hidden in sacred places for religion sake
                        <lb/>by men of all degrees. Pausanias reports that a brazen Skeleton of
                        <lb/>admirable artifice was hung at the top of the temple by Hippocrates.
                        <lb/>That famous Tripos was <orig>allso</orig> consecrated to Apollo by Pelops, at the
                        <lb/>time when <orig>hee</orig> <orig>marryed</orig> Hippodamia the daughter <choice><orig>Œnomaus</orig><reg>Oenomaus</reg></choice> King
                        <lb/>of Elis, which Tripos Mulciber made, and gave to Pelops: It was
                        <lb/>erected in the <orig>midle</orig> of the temple, in which Pythia sitting
                        
                        
                        
                        <pb n="145"/><fw>Discourse 46.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                        <lb/><choice><orig>receiv'd</orig><reg>received</reg></choice> the inspiration of the <choice><orig>Devill</orig><reg>Devil</reg></choice> gaping with a wide mouth, and then<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>prophesyd</orig>, and gave responses to those that <choice><orig>desird</orig><reg>desired</reg></choice> to know the events of things
                        <lb/>to come: Delphos was indeed in <choice><orig>Bœotica</orig><reg>Boeotica</reg></choice> seated about the foot of Parnassus.<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Near to the temple was the divining <orig>fountaine</orig>, named Cassiotis, which, if bur
                        <lb break="no"/>ning torches was brought to it did extinguish them: if they were removed
                        <lb/><orig>farre</orig> of, they were suddenly kindled, and <orig>tooke</orig> fire; and the water of<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>that <orig>fountaine</orig> being <orig>dranke</orig> <orig>yeilded</orig> the virtue of divining, but not
                        <lb break="no"/>withstanding the drinkers of that water were made of shorter life. Con
                        <lb break="no"/>course therefore being made from all parts of Europe and Asia to the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><choice><orig>Delphicke</orig><reg>Delphic</reg></choice> Oracle, the Poets <choice><orig>feigne</orig><reg>feign</reg></choice> that place, namely Parnassus to be<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>in the <orig>midle</orig> of the earth, and that they proved by an example of Jupi
                        <lb break="no"/>ter, who had experimented it by sending forth two Eagles: But this thing
                        <lb/>not being supported by the reputation of history, it is not derogatory from the
                        <lb/>truth, to ascribe it to <orig>Chymicall</orig> matters, especially Apollo being, as <orig>hath</orig> been<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>declared, <orig>alltogether</orig> <orig>Chymicall</orig> by <orig>originall</orig>, though the <choice><orig>Devill</orig><reg>Devil</reg></choice> afterwards<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>confirmed the superstition of men, and gave <orig>prophesyes</orig> under that name.
                        <lb/>The two Eagles are two stones, whereof one comes from the East, the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>other from the West, which the Philosophers have many <orig>wayes</orig> demonstra
                        <lb break="no"/>ted. Jupiter sends them forth, as his <choice><orig>Ensigne<c rend="double-hyphen">-</c>bearers</orig><reg>Ensign=bearers</reg></choice>. The Eagle seems in
                        <lb break="no"/>deed a <orig>freind</orig> to Apollo or the <orig>Sunne</orig>, in proving her chickens at the <orig>Sunne</orig>,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>which if they cannot endure, <orig>Shee</orig> <choice><orig>disownes</orig><reg>disowns</reg></choice> them as illegitimate. Its feathers
                        <lb/>being <orig>joyned</orig> with other things are <orig>sayd</orig> not to putrefy, and to <orig>devoure</orig>
                        <lb/>the feathers of other birds, easily admitting gilding <orig>allso</orig>: By old age, or
                        <lb/><choice><orig>sicknesse</orig><reg>sickness</reg></choice> it <orig>dyes</orig> not, but by famine; For the upper <orig>beake</orig> <orig>growes</orig> <choice><orig>soe</orig><reg>so</reg></choice>
                        <lb/>crooked that it cannot receive food: Which having cast off it <choice><orig>plungeth</orig><reg>plunges</reg></choice> <orig>it
                        <lb break="no"/>selfe</orig> three times in a <orig>fountaine</orig>, and <choice><orig>soe</orig><reg>so</reg></choice> is <orig>sayd</orig> to <orig>returne</orig> to youth.<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Hereupon <orig>sayth</orig> the Psalmist: Your youth shall be renewed as the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>youth of an Eagle: This of all birds is never affected with Lightening:
                        <lb/>It <orig>warrs</orig> with the dragon, which hunts after its eggs for the sake of<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>them: All the endowments of whose nature have <choice><orig>affoarded</orig><reg>afforded</reg></choice> the Philo
                        <lb break="no"/>sophers reason to <choice><orig>prædicate</orig><reg>predicate</reg></choice> the Eagle in their art, and assimilate the
                        <lb/>stone to it, whereof innumerable examples being obvious in their<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>books, <orig>wee</orig> will not here <choice><orig>alleadge</orig><reg>alleged</reg></choice> more<pc>. . . . . . . . . .</pc>
                    </ab>   
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>