<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="emblem" n="e02"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
                <pb n="11"/><!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                
                
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>
                        <lb/>Embleme 2. Of the Secrets of Nature.
                        <lb/>the earth is his Nurce.
                        
                    </head>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Epigramme 2.</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>A courteous Wolfe to Romulus displaye</l>
                        <l>Her milky duggs, to Jove a Goat, tis sayd:</l>
                        <l>Nor is it strange to assert our mother Earth</l>
                        <l>Gave sucke to th' tender philosophicke birth;</l>
                        <l>If beasts soe small Heroes soe great could breed,</l>
                        <l>How great will hee be, whome the <del>whose</del> earth doth feed!</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                
                
                <pb n="12"/> <!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Discourse 2.</head>
                    <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                        <lb/>It is concluded by the peripaleticks, and orthodox philosophers, that the<milestone unit="section" n="e02-01" /> <!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                        <lb/>thing nourishing is converted into the substance of the thing nourishes, and
                        <lb/>assimilated to it, not indeed before; but after the alteration of it, and that is ac
                        <lb break="no"/>counted an infallible axiome: for how would the thing nourishing (which is all
                        <lb break="no"/>ready before the like: or how should those things, which, cannot be assimilated
                        <lb/>to the thing nourished, be taken for nutriment, such as are wood, stones and
                        <lb/>the like! as therefore the first is vayne, soe the other is contrary to nature, but
                        <lb/>for an infant now borne to be nourished by the milke of animalls, is a thing
                        <lb/>not repugnant to nature: because assimilation of it may be made, but far
                        <lb/>more easily of the mothers, than of anothers: wherefore physicians doe con
                        <lb break="no"/>clude, that it conduceth to the health, similitude of substance and manners,
                        <lb/>as allso strength of an infant, if it be allways nourishes by the milke of its
                        <lb/>owne mother, on the contrary if by another. This is the harmony of every 
                        <lb/>nature, that like delights in its like, and followes its footsteps, foe farre as it
                        <lb/>is able, in all things, with a contains tacit consent and conspiration: the same
                        <lb/>thing usually happens in the naturall worke of the philosophers, which is aequally
                        <lb/>governed by nature in the conformation of it, as an infant in the mothers
                        <lb/>wombe, and though a father and mother, and nurce <del>Asecfe<unclear reason="illegible"></unclear></del>be by way of si
                        <lb break="no"/>militude ascribed to it, yet it is not more artificiall, than the generation of
                        <lb/>every animall: two seeds are by a certaine pleasant artifice joynd together
                        <lb/>by animalls, and both humane sexes, which being united doe by successive
                        <lb/>alteration produce an Embryo, which growes and is increased, acquires life
                        <lb/>and motion, and then is nourished by milke: but nocessary it is for the wo
                        <lb break="no"/>man in time of conception and impregnation to carry herselfe temperately
                        <lb/>in heat, meat and drinke, motion and rest, and other circumstances, otherwise
                        <lb/>an abortion will follow, and destruction of the conceived Embryo, which
                        <lb/>observation in six things not naturall, because it is praescribed by physi
                        <lb break="no"/>cians attending to their art, is allso artificiall. After the same manner if the
                        <lb/>seeds be not joynes together in the philosophicall worke, they ought to be
                        <lb/>joyned: but if they could be found somewhere joyned together, as the seed
                        <lb/>of the Locke and Henne are had in an egge subsisting together in one
                        <lb/>continent, then wouldthe philosophers worke be yet more naturalle, than
                        <lb/>the generation of animalls. But let us grant, as the philosophers doe assert,
                        <lb/>that one comes from the east and another from the west, and are made one,
                        <lb/>what more is administred to them, than mixti<subs><del>ire</del><add>on</add></subs><!-- unsure on this word -->in their owne vessell, tem
                        <lb break="no"/>perate heat and nutriment? the vessell is indeed artificiall, but herein is
                        <lb/>noe differente, whether the nest be made by the Henne herselfe, or dispo
                        <lb break="no"/>sed by a <subst><del>rusticke</del><add>country dame</add></subst> in <subst><del><unclear reason="illegible">envi</unclear></del><add>some</add></subst> certaine place, as comon it is, the generation of
                        <lb/>the eggs, and the hatching of chickens from them will be the same. Heat
                        <lb/>is a naturall thing, whether it proceed from the temperate fire of fur
                        <lb/>naces, and putrefaction of dung, or from the Sunne and aire, or bowells
                        <lb/>of the mother, or elswhere: thus the Aegyptian doth by art administer
                        
                        
                        
                        <pb n="16"/><fw>Discourse 3.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                        
                        <lb />
                        <pc>- - - - - </pc>
                        
                    </ab>   
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
