<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="emblem" n="e49"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
                <pb n="152"/><!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                
                
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>
                        <lb/><orig>Embleme</orig> 49. Of the Secrets of Nature.
                        <lb/>The <orig>Philosophicall</orig> infant is, as Orion, the <orig>Sonne</orig> of three fathers.
                    </head>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
                    <head><orig>Epigramme</orig> 49.</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>Vulcan with Hermes and Apollo did</l>
                        <l>Their seed inject into an oxes hide,</l>
                        <l>Whence produced was the great Orion:</l>
                        <l>Three fathers <orig>allso</orig> <orig>hath</orig> the <orig>Sophicke</orig> <orig>Sonne</orig>;</l>
                        <l>The <orig>Sunne</orig> is first, Vulcan the next is <choice><orig>stil'd</orig><reg>stilled</reg></choice></l>
                        <l>The artist is third father of this Child.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                
                
                <pb n="153"/> <!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Discourse 49.</head>
                    <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                        <lb/>Those women, which prostitute themselves to variety of men, <orig>doe</orig> <orig>sel<milestone unit="section" n="e03-01" /> <!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                        <lb break="no"/>dome</orig> conceive lively children through the confusion of <orig>divers</orig> seeds:<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>for nature in the generation of man and the most part of <orig>animalls</orig> <orig>ad
                        <lb break="no"/>mitts</orig> <orig>noe</orig> <choice><orig>superfætation</orig><reg>superfetation</reg></choice>, except perhaps very rarely: and therefore<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>every offspring is produced from one <orig>onely</orig> father and mother, whether
                        <lb/>it be one or more, as is <orig>allso</orig> manifest by <orig>historyes</orig> and the event of<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>some supposing otherwise; in the first place of Margarett the wife of
                        <lb/>Herman <choice><orig>Earle</orig><reg>Earl</reg></choice> of Henneberge, who, in the year 1276, brought forth
                        <lb/>three hundred and sixty five children, which were all baptized,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>and the males called by the name of John, and the females Eliza
                        <lb break="no"/>beth, their grave being dead is yet to be seen in the Church of Laus
                        <lb break="no"/>dune, one mile distant from the Hague towards the Sea in Holland,
                        <lb/>together with the brazen bason, in which they were baptized, and an
                        <lb/>inscription of the story: The cause <choice><orig>alleadgd</orig><reg>alleged</reg></choice> was, that the <choice><orig>Countesse</orig><reg>Countess</reg></choice>,
                        <lb/><orig>seing</orig> a poor woman carry two children <choice><orig>twinns</orig><reg>twins</reg></choice> in her <orig>armes</orig>, <orig>calld</orig> her
                        <lb/><choice><orig>adulteresse</orig><reg>adulteress</reg></choice>, as if it was impossible for more children to be <orig>borne</orig> at one
                        <lb/>conception by one man, but necessarily by <orig>severall</orig>: Whereupon an im
                        <lb break="no"/>precation being made by the poor woman, who knew her <orig>selfe</orig> clear<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>of that accusation, the <choice><orig>Countesse</orig><reg>Countess</reg></choice> conceived in her <orig>wombe</orig> at one time
                        <lb/>and by one man <choice><orig>soe</orig><reg>so</reg></choice> many children, as there are <orig>dayes</orig> in the year:
                        <lb/>This is indeed a miracle, but a <orig>naturall</orig> <orig>worke</orig>, which happened<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>through the vengeance of God: But in the <orig>Philosophicall</orig> <orig>worke</orig><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>that, which is otherwise contrary to nature, is easily admitted under
                        <lb/>the <choice><orig>veyle</orig><reg>veil</reg></choice> of an allegory: For here one infant is <orig>sayd</orig> to have three fa
                        <lb break="no"/>thers, or <orig>allso</orig> two, as <orig>allso</orig> mothers: Hereupon <orig>sayth</orig> Raymund cited by the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Rosary; Our infant <orig>hath</orig> two fathers and two mothers, and because <orig>hee</orig>
                        <lb/>with his whole substance is tenderly nourished in fire, <orig>hee</orig> therefore<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>never <orig>dyes</orig>: <orig>Soe</orig> <orig>Dionysus</orig> or Bacchus is <orig>sayd</orig> to have two mothers, who<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>was <choice><orig>rip'd</orig><reg>ripped</reg></choice> out of his mothers belly (being burned) before the time of his
                        <lb/>maturity, and matured in his fathers thigh, <choice><orig>soe</orig><reg>so</reg></choice> that the father became
                        <lb/>a mother: But these things are better declared in the conception of<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Orion, who is <orig>sayd</orig> to be produced from the seed of Apollo, Vulcan,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>and Mercury <orig>mixd</orig> together, and <orig>præservd</orig> in the hide of an Oxe for
                        <lb/>the space of <orig>tenne</orig> <orig>moneths</orig>: These things would be <orig>alltogether</orig> mon<note place="margin"><unclear reason="illegible">NBow</unclear></note>
                        <lb break="no"/>strous, not <orig>onely</orig> fabulous, if a secret of nature were not compre
                        <lb break="no"/>hended under these shrouds, not obvious to all Men. Lully in the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><choice><orig>Theoricke</orig><reg>Theoric</reg></choice> of his Testament attributes to the same <orig>Philosophicall</orig><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>infant <choice><orig>soe</orig><reg>so</reg></choice> many and <orig>allmost</orig> the same fathers, namely Sol, who
                        <lb/>is Apollo, or the <orig>cælestiall</orig> Sol is the first author of this generation,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>certaine</orig> matter <orig>knowne</orig> to the Philosophers, as upon the matrix<pc>-</pc>
                        
                        
                        
                        <pb n="154"/><fw>Discourse 49.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                        <lb/>of a woman, and therein <choice><orig>produceth</orig><reg>produces</reg></choice> a <orig>Sonne</orig> or infant like to <orig>himselfe</orig>,
                        <lb/>to <orig>whome</orig> afterwards <orig>hee</orig> will leave and <choice><orig>resigne</orig><reg>resign</reg></choice> his <orig>armes</orig> and ensigns<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>of virtues, by <choice><orig>paternall</orig><reg>paternal</reg></choice> right, that is, the faculty of maturing things im
                        <lb break="no"/>mature, and the energy of tinging and purging things not tinged nor
                        <lb/>purged. For whatsoever Sol is able to perfect in a thousand years, that
                        <lb/>will his <orig>Sonne</orig> <orig>performe</orig> in <choice><orig>halfe</orig><reg>half</reg></choice> an <orig>houre</orig>; That therefore virtue<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>may be made a thousand times stronger in him, than in Sol, his fa
                        <lb break="no"/>ther delivers him to Vulcan and the Artist together for education, that<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>his generous disposition may be polished and <orig>multiplyd</orig> in virtues by
                        <lb/>their means; for manifest it is that to practice from a child <choice><orig>conduceth</orig><reg>conduces</reg></choice>
                        <lb/>much: <orig>Soe</orig> Achilles, Jason, Hercules were <orig>coḿitted</orig> to Chiron to be in
                        <lb break="no"/>structed for the same end. For Milo the Crotonian, who being a boy<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>carryed</orig> a <choice><orig>calfe</orig><reg>calf</reg></choice>, when a man <orig>carryed</orig> an Oxe by <orig>custome</orig>. Besides Sol,
                        <lb/>Vulcan and the artist are not <choice><orig>erroniously</orig><reg>erroneously</reg></choice> reputed the fathers of this
                        <lb/>child, because as <orig>hee</orig> was the first, they made him to be such and <choice><orig>soe</orig><reg>so</reg></choice>
                        <lb/>great: <orig>Noe</orig> <orig>æquivalent</orig> compensation can be made to Masters for in
                        <lb break="no"/>stitution, as neither reward to parents for generation. These compose
                        <lb/>the body, those the mind. If the mind be better than the body, <orig>noe</orig>
                        <lb/><orig>lesse</orig> <choice><orig>recompence</orig><reg>recompense</reg></choice> is due to those, than to these. In the production of<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Orion Mercury contributed matter, Apollo <orig>forme</orig>, and Vulcan heat, or
                        <lb/>the <orig>externall</orig> efficient cause: <orig>Soe</orig> <orig>allso</orig> in the <orig>Philosophicall</orig> <orig>worke</orig>
                        <lb/>it is proper for three fathers to be seen to have conspired for the pro
                        <lb break="no"/>creation of one infant, in <orig>whome</orig> the Philosophers take great delight.
                    </ab>   
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>