<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="emblem" n="e03"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
                <pb n="29"/><!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                
                
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>
                        <lb/><orig>Embleme</orig> 8. Of the Secrets of Nature.
                        <lb/>Take an <orig>egge</orig> and smite it with a fiery sword.
                        
                    </head>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
                    <head><orig>Epigramme</orig> 8.</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>Rest not till you have found that <orig>egge</orig> <orig>soe</orig> rare,</l>
                        <l>Descended from the <choice><orig>loftyest</orig><reg>loftiest</reg></choice> bird <choice><orig>oth'</orig><reg>of the</reg></choice> <orig>aire</orig>:</l>
                        <l>With fire and <orig>steele</orig> (<orig>noe</orig> otherwise) confound</l>
                        <l>The Slimy white which <orig>dos</orig> the <choice><orig>yolke</orig><reg>yolk</reg></choice> surround;</l>
                        <l>Though to the God of fire Mars agd Shall give,</l>
                        <l>The product will of both the victor live.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                
                
                <pb n="30"/> <!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Discourse 8.</head>
                    <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                        <lb/>Many and <orig>severall</orig> sorts of birds there are, which as they are indefinite in number, <orig>soe</orig><milestone unit="section" n="e03-01" /> <!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                        <lb/>are they <orig>unknowne</orig> to us by names: Story tells us of a very great bird appearing at a<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>certaine</orig> time of the year in a small Isle of the Sea called Ruc, because it can lift
                        <lb/>up an Elephant with it into the <orig>aire</orig>. India and America <orig>doe</orig> <choice><orig>yeild</orig><reg>yield</reg></choice> <choice><orig>Parrotts</orig><reg>Parrots</reg></choice> of va
                        <lb break="no"/>rious <orig>colour</orig>, Crows, and the like: but it is not the <orig>Philosophicall</orig> intention to in
                        <lb break="no"/>quire after the eggs of these birds: The <choice><orig>Ægyptians</orig><reg>Egyptians</reg></choice> <orig>doe</orig> yearly infest, and as it<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>were with a <orig>publicke</orig> <orig>warre</orig> denounced prosecute the Eggs of Crocodiles with<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>weapons of iron; the Philosophers <orig>doe</orig> <choice><orig>burne</orig><reg>burn</reg></choice> their <orig>egge</orig> with fire, not to mortify<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>and destroy it, but that it may receive life and growth; for when a chicken is<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>from <orig>theme</orig> produced animated and living, it cannot be <orig>sayd</orig> to be the corruption
                        <lb/>but generation of it: it <choice><orig>ceaseth</orig><reg>ceases</reg></choice> indeed to be an <orig>egge</orig> by the privation of the <choice><orig>ovall</orig><reg>oval</reg></choice>
                        <lb/><orig>forme</orig>, and begins to be an <orig>animall</orig> with two feet and volatile by the introduction
                        <lb/>of a more noble <orig>forme</orig>: In an <orig>egge</orig> are the seeds of both male and female<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>joyned</orig> together under one cover or shell: The <choice><orig>yolke</orig><reg>yolk</reg></choice> constitutes the chicken,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>and the <orig>radicall</orig> parts and <orig>bowells</orig> thereof, the seed of the male being the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>former, and <orig>internall</orig> efficient: The white <orig>yeilds</orig> matter, or thread and incre
                        <lb break="no"/>ment to the rudiment as it were to the warp of the chicken: <orig>Externall</orig> heat
                        <lb/>is the first mover, which <orig>doth</orig> by a <orig>certaine</orig> circulation of the Elements, toge
                        <lb break="no"/>ther with instinct and guidance of nature introduce a new <orig>forme</orig> by<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>changing one thing into another: for water turnes into <orig>aire</orig>, <orig>aire</orig> into fire, and
                        <lb/>fire into earth, upon the conjunction of which, a <choice><orig>specificke</orig><reg>specific</reg></choice> <orig>forme</orig> being trans
                        <lb break="no"/>mitted by the <orig>Starrs</orig>, an <orig>individuall</orig> is made of a <orig>certaine</orig> kind of bird, namely
                        <lb/>of that, whose <orig>egge</orig> it was, and seed infused in it. Is it indeed <orig>sayd</orig> to be smitten
                        <lb/>with a fiery sword, whilst Vulcan officiating the duty of a midwife gives pas
                        <lb break="no"/>sage or <choice><orig>egresse</orig><reg>egress</reg></choice> to the chicken by his axe, as to Pallas out of the <choice><orig>braine</orig><reg>brain</reg></choice> of Ju
                        <lb break="no"/>piter: This is that which Basill Valentine affirms, that Mercury was impri
                        <lb break="no"/>soned by Vulcan at the <orig>coḿand</orig> of Mars, and not released, before <orig>hee</orig> was<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/><orig>wholy</orig> <choice><orig>putrefyd</orig><reg>putrified</reg></choice> and dead: but this death is to him the <orig>begining</orig> of a new life,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>as the corruption or death of an <orig>egge</orig> brings new generation and life to the<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>chicken, <orig>soe</orig> an Embryo being freed from that <orig>humane</orig> vegetable life (which
                        <lb/>alone <orig>hee</orig> enjoyed in his mothers <orig>wombe</orig>, another more perfect is obtained by
                        <lb/>coming into the light of this world, as by nativity: yea <orig>allso</orig> <orig>wee</orig> being de
                        <lb break="no"/>prived of this present life, which <orig>wee</orig> lead, another most perfect and <choice><orig>æter
                        <lb break="no"/>nall</orig><reg>eternal</reg></choice> is at hand: Thus Lully <orig>doth</orig> in many places call this fiery sword a<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Sharp Spear; because fire <orig>doth</orig> as a Sharp Spear or sword perforate <orig>bodyes</orig>,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>and make them porous and pervious, that water can penetrate to dissolve
                        <lb/>and reduce them from <choice><orig>hardnesse</orig><reg>hardness</reg></choice> to <choice><orig>softnesse</orig><reg>softness</reg></choice> and tractability. In the
                        <lb/><choice><orig>Stomacke</orig><reg>Stomach</reg></choice> of a Cormorant, which is of all birds most voracious, are found
                        <lb/>long and round <choice><orig>wormes</orig><reg>worms</reg></choice> alive, which are to it as the instrument of heat,
                        <lb/>they forthwith invading, and as most sharp noodles perforating, (as <orig>wee</orig>
                        <lb/>have sometimes observed) and <orig>soe</orig> in a very short time consuming<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>the <choice><orig>Eeles</orig><reg>Eels</reg></choice> and other fish taken by it, with a <orig>wonderfull</orig> operation of na
                        <lb break="no"/>ture: as therefore heat <choice><orig>pricketh</orig><reg>pricks</reg></choice>, <orig>soe</orig> a thing pricking sometimes <choice><orig>supplys</orig><reg>supplies</reg></choice> the
                        
                        
                        
                        <pb n="31"/><fw>Discourse 8.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                        <lb/>place of heat: upon which consideration that, wherewith the Philosophers <orig>egge</orig><pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>ought to be pieced and smitten, may not undeservedly be called a fiery sword:
                        <lb/>but the Philosophers had rather have it understood of a temperate heat, where
                        <lb break="no"/>by the <orig>egge</orig> is kept <orig>warme</orig>, as Morfolens in Turba declares, saying, wise men
                        <lb/>ought to <orig>burne</orig> away moisture first with a slow fire, as is <choice><orig>Shewed</orig><reg>Showed</reg></choice> to us by an
                        <lb/>example in the generation of a chicken, and where the fire is augmented,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>the <orig>vessell</orig> must be <choice><orig>stopd</orig><reg>stopped</reg></choice> on all sides, that the body of the <orig>brasse</orig>, and the
                        <lb/>fugitive Spirit thereof may not exhale. But what birds was the <orig>egge</orig>? Mos
                        <lb break="no"/>cus in the same plate; now I Say, <orig>sayth</orig> <orig>hee</orig>, that <orig>noe</orig> instruments are<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>made, except of our white, starry, splendid powder, and of the white<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>stone, of which powder are made <choice><orig>fitt</orig><reg>fit</reg></choice> instruments for the <orig>egge</orig>; yet they
                        <lb/>have not named the <orig>egge</orig>, nor what birds the <orig>egge</orig> was<pc>. . . . .</pc>
                    </ab>   
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

