<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="emblem" n="e30"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
                <pb n="95"/><!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                
                
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>
                        <lb/>Embleme 30. Of the Secrets of Nature.
                        <lb/>Luna is as requisite to Sol as a henne to a cocke.
                    </head>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Epigramme 30.</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>What can you doe dear Sol! alone, if I</l>
                        <l>Joyne not as henne with cocke to multiply?</l>
                        <l>Or can I Luna Natures guifts expresse</l>
                        <l>Without your ayde? noe, grant mee some redresse.</l>
                        <l>Hee's but a foole those to confine apart</l>
                        <l>Whome Nature would have joynd in mind and heart.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                
                
                <pb n="96"/> <!-- Change to page number of the actual manuscript -->
                <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Discourse 30.</head>
                    <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                        <lb/>Avicenne in his booke of the Soule divers times admonisheth, that noe<pc>-</pc><milestone unit="section" n="e03-01" /> <!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                        <lb/>eggs are to be taken for art, but onely of those henns, which had a cock:
                        <lb/>that is, the fæminine subject avayles nothing without the masculine<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>virtue, and on the contrary, nor a cocke profitable without a henne:
                        <lb/>for both these sexes must be joynd together in the Philosophicall coupe,
                        <lb/>that multiplication may be made: The Philosophers doe indeed use
                        <lb/>the similitude taken from a cocke, because in the first place hee is<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>more correspondent to the power of Sulphur, than any other male of
                        <lb/>birds, one being able to serve many henns, and not easily suffering a
                        <lb/>rivall in the same dunghill, thinking himselfe convenient and suffi
                        <lb break="no"/>cient for everyone. Hee is the bird of Mars, transformd, as the Poets
                        <lb/>fable, from the youth Gallus, who was entrusted to observe Sol, that<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>hee might not discover the adultery of Mars with Venus, and very
                        <lb/>Martiall in fight, contending with his adversary even to death: In<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>the Philosophicall worke hee repræsents Sol, as the henne doth Luna:
                        <lb/>there is therefore the same necessity of joyning Sol with Luna, as a<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>cocke with a henne: The cocke is allso consecrated to Sol, at whose<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>approach hee riseth, and goes to sleep with him: hee often looks up to<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>heaven, and erects his hooked tayle upright: hee fights against Serpents in
                        <lb/>defence of his henns: hee is an acceptable messenger of light and Latona<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>being præsent at her labour: Latona indeed brought forth Sol and Luna,
                        <lb/>and therefore hee is appropriated to the mother and Sonne: But Sol,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Luna, and Latona doe in Chymicall subjects agree, soe allso the cocke
                        <lb/>and henne: but these allso proceded from an egge, and againe doe<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>lay eggs for the production of young chickens; soe allso doe the Philoso
                        <lb break="no"/>phers eggs turne into birds of the same kind, provided they be kept<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>warme with temperate heat, as is the heat of a brooding henne, which
                        <lb/>endures continually: For whereas amongst other birds the male allso
                        <lb/>sitts upon the eggs, the cocke alone shews himselfe free from this
                        <lb/>office or burthen; and therefore all the care and pains of hatching the
                        <lb/>eggs, and producing chickens lyes upon the henne; where her sedulity
                        <lb/>and diligence may be observed, how hastily Shee eats and drinks, and
                        <lb/>unloads her belly, and presently runns backe to her eggs, before they be<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>cold: Then with what force and violence Shee defends her chickens,
                        <lb/>with what tendernesse Shee receives and covers them being naked under
                        <lb/>her wings, with what a voyce, as with a bell, Shee calls and keeps them<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>together, with what study Shee breaks the harder crums or seeds for<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>them, and præsents them with her beake, as on a knife, this worke of<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>nature is worthy of admiration. And all these things are, that man
                        <lb/>may neither want eggs nor chickens for aliment: After the same man
                        <lb break="no"/>ner the Philosopher or artist doth most diligently and providently<pc>-</pc>
                        
                        
                        
                        <pb n="97"/><fw>Discourse 30.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                        <lb/>proceed in all his operations; For hee picks up eggs there where a cocke<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>hath been, trying them whether they be adle, after that hee cleanseth<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>præpares, and disposseth them in his vessells, as nests, and administers due
                        <lb/>heat, whereby the subjects mixd together daily act and suffer one by<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>another, till after a long time passing through various colours they come
                        <lb/>to one colour and essence: In which operation Solution, congulation,
                        <lb/>Sublimation, ascension, descension, distillation, calcination and fixion
                        <lb/>as intermediate are perfected: for a hard and compact thing cannot<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>be altered, therefore Solution is præmised, that is may be made liquid
                        <lb/>and soft: and where a thing is dissolved, it is convenient allso to be<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>coagulated, not to its former hardnesse but a honyish tractability;<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Sublimation separates the pure from the impure, and makes a thing
                        <lb/>vile more worthy, the inferiour superiour; and therefore this nei
                        <lb break="no"/>ther ought to be wanting, for it is as the mistresse and directresse<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>of all: when sublimation is made, some parts ascend higher, which
                        <lb/>is ascension, and others againe descend, and soe descension is made:
                        <lb/>Distillation allso clarifyes the whole being often interposed, and that
                        <lb/>which remaynes in the bottome is calcined: then both are fixed, and
                        <lb/>soe the worke is completed. But if a man gather all these parti
                        <lb break="no"/>cular operations under a generall, which is Coction, hee will not<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>erre much from the purpose: for as soe many chickens as there are,
                        <lb/>which runne here and there dispersedly, doe resort to one mother or
                        <lb/>nurce the henne, soe doe soe many severall wayes of operating con
                        <lb break="no"/>curre to the womans worke, that is, coction alone: It is Luna, which<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>comes to be exalted to the sublimity of Sol, for whose sake all these
                        <lb/>things are done, that is, durable matrimony is intended between Sol<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>and Luna, which if effected, all legations, desponsations, copulations,
                        <lb/>dubitatious, ex. will cease. and the bed and flesh of both will be one,
                        <lb/>mutuall and constant love, æternall peace, and an indissoluble alli
                        <lb break="no"/>ance: Sol without Luna is of noe great esteeme, and Luna without
                        <lb/>Sol of meane and sordid condition: But Shee receives splendour, and
                        <lb/>dignity, with strength or constancy of mind and body from Sol her<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>husband, and Sol from Luna multiplication of offspring, and pro
                        <lb break="no"/>pagation of kind: hereupon Sayth the Rosary: If onely one of them<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>Should be in our stone, the medicine would never flow easily, nor,<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>yeild the tincture, and if it should yeild, it would not tinge, unlesse
                        <lb/>for see much as allso the remainder would be, and the Mercury would
                        <lb/>evaporate in fume, because the receptacle of the tincture would not
                        <lb/>be in it: And Geber in his booke of examinations proves, that if Sol<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>and Luna be incorporated together with art, they are not easily<pc>-</pc>
                        <lb/>separated<pc>. . . . . . . . . . . .</pc>
                    </ab>   
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
