<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="emblem" n="e04"><!-- Change the value of n to "e" followed by the number of the emblem. Use two digits for all numbers. -->
            <pb n="17"/><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript -->
            
            
            <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
               <head>
                  <lb/>Embleme 4. Of the Secrets of Nature.
                  <lb/>Joyne the Brother with the Sister and give them a cup of love.                  
               </head>
            </div>
            
            
            <div type="epigram" xml:lang="en">
               <head>Epigramme 4.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>To multiply the world with humane race,</l>
                  <l>The brother <subst><del>must</del><add>did</add></subst> his sister close embrace:</l>
                  <l>Set therefore one the other freindly wed,</l>
                  <l>That they may act as man and wife in bed:</l>
                  <l>First to incite, praepare a cup o'th best,</l>
                  <l>And then they both will freely doe the rest.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            
            
            <pb n="18"/> <!-- Page number of the actual manuscript -->
            <div type="discourse" xml:lang="en">
               <head>Discourse 4.</head>
               <ab><!--Our convention will be that if we have break = "no" then it means that the word is broken across the line with a dash--> 
                  <lb/>The divine and politicall lawes doe both fordid those people to marry, who are by<milestone unit="section" n="e04-01" /> <!-- Change the value of n to "e" plus the number of the emblem (in two digits), followed by a hyphen and then a two-digit count of sentence -->
                  <lb/>nature joyned in too near a degree of consanguinity, such namely as <add>directly</add>ascend and des
                  <lb break="no"/>cend in a genealogicall line, and that for very good considerations; but when the 
                  <lb/>philosophers speake of the mother to be joynd with the Sonne, or father with the
                  <lb/>daughter, or of the brother with the sister, they neither say or doe anything contrary
                  <lb/>to the sayd laws: because subjects distinguish attributes and causes effects; for the
                  <lb/>persons of philosophers are <add>as</add>free from those differences as <del>well as</del>the sonns and daugh
                  <lb break="no"/>ters of Adam, who marryed one with another without the imputation of any
                  <lb/>crime: but the principall reason seems to be, that man=kind might be more
                  <lb/>firmly united and linked in affinity and freindship, and not <del>be</del>divided into
                  <lb/>inimicall and haereditary factions of familyes: the same reason remaining
                  <lb/>firme and entire in the first sonns and daughters of Adam, did not as all de
                  <lb break="no"/>barre them from the <subst><del>rights</del><add>rites</add></subst>of matrimony: for man=kind did then exist in
                  <lb/>them alone, and noe others were living besides them, and their parents, and
                  <lb/>therefore as allyid in blood, soe necessarily were they joyned in affinity: but
                  <lb/>a multitudeof men increasing, and being distributed into innumerable fa
                  <lb break="no"/>milyes, this was found a true and just cause why brothers should not marry
                  <lb/>sisters: The philosophers have another reason, why sisters may marry
                  <lb/>brothers, namely the similitude of substance, that it may be joyned to
                  <lb/>the like: but in this kind there are onely two like one anotheras to species,
                  <lb/>different as to sex, whereof one is saluted by the name of brother, the
                  <lb/>other of sister: they therefore may be the same both liberty and condi
                  <lb break="no"/>tion, yea and inevitable necessity, as the first consanguine men, be lawfully
                  <lb/>comitted to one matrimony: the brother is hott and dry, and therefore ve
                  <lb break="no"/>ry cholericke: the sister is cold and moist, having much phlegmaticke
                  <lb/>matter in her: which natures soe differing in temper doe comonly best
                  <lb/>agree in love and fruitfullnesse, and the propagation of Children: for as
                  <lb/>fire, which may be propagates, is not easily strucke out of the most hard
                  <lb/>body steel and steel, nor out of the brittle flint and flint, but out of hard
                  <lb/>and brittle, that is, steel and fling, soe a lively offspring is not produ
                  <lb break="no"/>ced from a hott man and fiery woman, as neither from both cold (for the
                  <lb/>coldnesse of the man is barrenesse) but from him hott, her more cold,
                  <lb/>for, in the latitude of humane temperament, the hottest woman is con
                  <lb break="no"/>cludes colder than the coldest man of his sex, if sound, as Lev. Lemnius
                  <lb/>in lib. de occ. nat. mirat. proves: the sister therefore and brother are
                  <lb/>rightly joyned together by the philosophers: If a man defines offspring
                  <lb/>from a henne, bitch, shee goat, Ewe, or other brutes, hee joynes a <del>dogge</del>
                  <lb/>cocke, dogge, hee goat, ramme, every animall to its species, to which it is most like, and soe is not frustrated of his desire; nor indeed doth hee
                  <lb/>respect the consanguinity of brutes, but onely the generosity of every
                  <lb/>one, and the congruity of nature: soe may it be sayd of the body of a tree,
                  <lb/>and the slippe to be therein grafted, yea of the metallicke
                  
                  
       
                  <pb n="19"/><fw>Discourse 4.</fw><!-- Page number of the actual manuscript, followed by the header on the page. -->
                  <lb/>nature, which notwithstanding as it hath of all things the greatest
                  <lb/>similitude and homogeneity of substance, doth soe require, where it
                  <lb/>desires a thing to be joyned with it: But brother and sister being joynd
                  <lb/>together, doe not become fruitfull, nor persist long in love, extept a philo
                  <lb break="no"/>thesium, or cup of love be administred to them like an amorous potion:
                  <lb/>for their minds are hereby soe quieted and united, that (laying aside mo
                  <lb break="no"/>desty) they doe as it were drunke (like Lot) goe together, and procreate
                  <lb/>an offspring (not spurious but) legitimate: For who knowes not that man
                  <lb break="no"/>kind is very much obliged to medicine, because many thousands of men
                  <lb/>are now in the world, which would not have been, if their fathers or fore
                  <lb break="no"/>fathers had not by the means and benefit thereof been freed and delivered
                  <lb/>from the defect of sterility, or their mothers <add>praeserves</add>from abortion, by removing
                  <lb/>and taking away the cause, or the nearest, and remote impediment? This
                  <lb/>cup of love is therfore given to this new marryd couple for the same reasons,
                  <lb/>which any man may hereby plainly understand are three, that is to say,
                  <lb/>constancy of love, remotion of sterility, and praevention of abortion
              
                  <lb />
                     <pc>- - - - - </pc>
                  
               </ab>   
            </div>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
